<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The tempestuous soul calmed by Jesus Christ; being an extract of several sermons, / preached by Anthony Palmer, pastor of the church at Bourton on the Water in Gloucester-shire.</title>
            <author>Palmer, Anthony, 1618?-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90691</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P219</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1496_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208632</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867563</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867563</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119879</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90691)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119879)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 192:E1496[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The tempestuous soul calmed by Jesus Christ; being an extract of several sermons, / preached by Anthony Palmer, pastor of the church at Bourton on the Water in Gloucester-shire.</title>
                  <author>Palmer, Anthony, 1618?-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 107, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A.M. for E. Brewster and G. Sawbridge, and are to be sold at the signe of the Bible on Ludgate-hill.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLIII. [1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 7"; an extra "I" has been added in MS. at end of Roman numeral imprint date.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119879:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119879:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TEMPESTUOUS SOUL CALMED BY Jeſus Chriſt; BEING An Extract of ſeverall SERMONS, PREACHED By ANTHONY PALMER, Paſtor of the Church at <hi>Bourton</hi> on the Water in <hi>Glouceſter-ſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. M.</hi> for <hi>E. Brewſter</hi> and <hi>G. Saw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Signe of the Bible on Ludgate-hill. MDCLIIII</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:119879:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119879:2"/>
            <head>To my dear Father, Brothers, and Siſters, and others of my Beloved Kindred and Friends, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I know my own heart, there were two Reaſons prevailed with me for ſending forth this Treatiſe into the light; Firſt, to witneſſe what the Lord (to the praiſe of his abundant grace) hath done for my own poor ſoul. Secondly, As drawn forth by tender affections and yern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bowels, I deſire more and more to put on for your immortall ſouls, which my hearts deſire is ſhould be as dear and pretious to me as my own, yea, that my heart might be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with that zeal of holy <hi>Paul,</hi> Rom. 11.14. <hi>If by any means I may provoke to emulation them which are of my fleſh, and might ſave ſome of them.</hi> In this brief Treatiſe (though chiefly pointing at the comforting a diſquieted ſpirit) yet there is laid down in the former part of it what
<pb facs="tcp:119879:3"/>may ſuit with your ſeverall conditions, and ſo to ſet up a reſt leſſe enquiry in your ſpirits after the Lord Jeſus, till he ſhall fill your ſouls with this bleſſed calm of his own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence here ſhadowed forth unto you: If it ſhould be objected by any other, that I might have directed you to other Books before ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant (of which bleſſed be God there's abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant choice;) I anſwer, and I verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve will you with me, that the room I have in your affections will render ſomething from my ſelf (though far ſhort of the excellencies of other Pieces) more gratefull to you, and that you will be the more inclined to reade it; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon which account I ſend it to you, with my breathings to heaven for the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Spirit of grace to be with it; and all others to whoſe hands it ſhall come, cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a candid interpretation with them: I Reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, moſt affectionately in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>A. P.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Bourton</hi> on the Water, <date>
                     <hi>Sept.</hi> 21. 1652.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>July 12. 1653.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Joſeph Caryl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119879:3"/>
            <head>The Tempeſtuous Soul Calmed by Jeſus Chriſt.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>MAT. 8.23,24,25,26,27.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And when he was entred into a Ship, his Diſciples followed him.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And behold, there aroſe a great tempeſt in the Sea, inſomuch that the Ship was covered with the waves: but he was aſleep.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And his Diſciples came to him, and awoke him, ſaying, Lord ſave us, we periſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And he ſaith unto them, Why are ye fearfull, O ye of little faith? Then he aroſe and rebuked the windes and the Sea, and there was a great calm.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But the men marvelled, ſaying, What manner of man is this that even the windes and the Sea obey him?</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Words contain an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire work and miracle of the Lord Chriſt, ſo that we need not look for co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence; They are uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly held forth by Divines to ſet forth the preſence of the Lord Jeſus
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:119879:4"/>with his Church in all the tempeſts that come upon it; which, if I conceive, may without wreſting be alſo uſed to diſcover the preſence of Chriſt calming a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſoul in all the tempeſts that befall it; At leaſt, by way of Allegory it will hold; as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith there is ſuch a ſpirituall uſe to be made of every miracle of the Lord Chriſts.</p>
               <p>And in this ſenſe I ſhall make uſe of them, and ſo unfold them into theſe ſix Ohſervations. <list>
                     <item>1. When Jeſus Chriſt draws in a Soul to himſelf, he uſually raiſeth a tempeſt in that ſoul. <hi>There aroſe a tempeſt,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>2. The Soul when thus in a tempeſt, it comes in a periſhing condition to Jeſus Chriſt. <hi>Lord ſave us, we periſh.</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>3. Jeſus Christ ſeems for a time to take no notice of a ſoul in ſuch a tempeſt and periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing condition. <hi>He was aſleep,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>4. True faith may be mixt with much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and fear, and yet may engage the heart of Chriſt to ſuccour; <hi>Why are ye fearfull, O ye of little faith.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5. A word from Chriſt can rebuke that tempeſt upon a Soul. <hi>He rebuked the windes,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
                     <item>6. The Soul that is thus calmed is filled
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119879:4"/>with the wonders of Chriſts power and love; <hi>They marvelled, ſaying, What manner of man is this that the windes and Sea obey him?</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe I ſhall open in their order.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="observation">
               <p>
                  <hi>When Chriſt draws in a Soul to himſelf he uſually raiſeth a tempeſt in that ſoul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The word for a <hi>tempeſt</hi> in the Originall is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which properly ſignifies an Earthquake which cauſeth a ſhaking of che Earth; The ſame word is uſed by the Septuagint in <hi>Ezekiel</hi> frequently to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie a ruſhing winde, a noiſe, a ſhaking: Now then this doth very well fit our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to diſcover this tempeſt upon a poor ſoul as drawing in to Chriſt, which is a kinde of earthquake, a ſhaking of an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy heart (whoſe principles and aims were earthly) as promiſed by the Lord Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11.4. <hi>And he ſhall ſmite the earth with the rod of his mouth,</hi> when he comes in with a ruſhing, and a noiſe, like the voice in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Viſion, <hi>Cap.</hi> 3.22. when the awakenings and enlightenings of the Word and voice of God fall in (ſhaking the ſpirit of a dead ſinner) like the noiſe of many waters, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15, Thus when the fear of a miſcarrying ſoul laies hold upon it, ſuch a kinde of ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119879:5"/>and tempeſt is upon it. Now the Lord ordereth it to be thus with a Soul for theſe Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. God cauſeth a glimpſe of his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to paſſe by a Soul, that the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by ſuch a reflexion from God, may ſee in ſome meaſure what ſin hath done upon him, at what an infinite diſtance it hath ſet him at with the moſt holy God, how unlike unto him ſin hath made him; That he may in ſome meaſure ſee and feel what he is, when the great and righteous God takes him in hand, which makes him ready to cry out with <hi>Peter</hi> at the appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Chriſt to him, <hi>Depart from me, for I am a ſinfull man,</hi> Luk. 5.8. And as <hi>Moſes</hi> in his ſelf-abaſement, when God appeared to him, <hi>Exod.</hi> 3.6. Moſes <hi>hid his face for he was afraid to look upon God:</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> 11. <hi>Who am I that thou ſhouldſt ſend me?</hi> A glimpſe of God cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſuch an abaſement upon a ſoul, and even a ſhaking to be upon it, That the creature may magnifie the greatneſs and purity of God, and be vile in its own eyes before him: This is the firſt Reaſon of it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He raiſeth ſuch a tempeſt and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king upon a ſinfull worm, To cauſe him
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:119879:5"/>in part to taſte what a bitter cup it was, he could ſo delightfully and boldly quaſſe of, yea, to have a taſte of that bitter cup that Jeſus Chriſt drank brim full of his fathers wrath, that if one dram of it be ſo unſupportable to a ſoul, what were the full vials of it that were poured forth upon the ſinleſs ſoul and body of Chriſt? that thence when we come to ſee him we may be pierced and be in bitterneſſe for him.</p>
               <p n="3">Yea 3. That a Soul may truly and in earneſt feel and diſcern its need of ſuch a Jeſus to bear and deliver from that wrath; When ſuch a glimpſe of God upon it, ſuch a ſhaking, ſuch an abaſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in its own vileneſſe, ſuch a taſting of wrath, then a Chriſt to quiet and calm a deſolate ſoul is worth looking after in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
               <p>But it will preſently be enquired whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther every Soul is brought into Chriſt this way?</p>
               <p>I will firſt open the height of this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt upon a Soul, and then I will ſatisfie this Query. It is thus, When God mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters up our ſins, and ſets them in order before our eyes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.21. When he will make ſin appear exceeding ſinfull to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:119879:6"/>be <hi>abounding ſin;</hi> When God writes bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things againſt a Soul, and makes it to poſſeſſe the iniquity of its youth; I need ſeek no further then the 38. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> for this tempeſt, and the 88. In both of them you have a deſcription of this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt upon a poor creature; <hi>Thine arrows ſtick faſt in me, There is no reſt in my bones becauſe of my ſin; Mine iniquities are gone over my head, and are a burthen too heavy for me to bear; Troubled, and bowed down, and go mourning all the day, filled with his terrours,</hi> as <hi>Heman:</hi> To this (as it may be conceived to have been the caſe with <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Heman,</hi> in both theſe Pſalmes) is uſually added ſome ſharp af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, either of ſickneſſe, or of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bittering ſome choice creature-comfort our ſpirits were inordinately let out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, which cauſeth this ſhaking and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt to be the more grievous, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come (as <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks) even as broken veſſels under the mighty hand of God.</p>
               <p>This alſo, by the ſufferance of God, is often heightned by Satans violent aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, black and horrible ſuggeſtions, blaſphemous accuſations, repreſenting ſin as unpardonable, joyns with an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing conſcience and all our fleſhly rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119879:6"/>that God is in a way of deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and beginning of wrath here, and therefore is apt to ſuggeſt ſelf-deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, ſo croſſing Gods deſign, perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Soul to fly from God as an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, when Gods main deſign is mercy to turn it to him.</p>
               <p>Now then, take all theſe, the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a great and holy and terrible God, ſhaking a poor earthly creature, the powerfull awakenings and enlightenings of his Word, a ſenſe of his fierce wrath, the dread of a miſcarrying ſoul, the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of ſin, the accuſations of conſcience, the afflicting hand of God, the deſperate aſſaults of Satan, theſe like ſeveral windes make a tempeſt in the whole man, and make it to cry out, <hi>Thy waves, O Lord, and thy billows go over my ſoul, who is able to abide thine appearance?</hi> Theſe, like ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall windes meeting in a cranny of the earth, make a concuſſion and mighty ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king upon the ſpirit of a ſinner, when the Lord thus takes him in hand.</p>
               <p>Now to anſwer the queſtion, whether every Soul be brought in to Chriſt ſuch a way in the height of this tempeſt?</p>
               <p>This is more then I dare aſſert, yet that many a poor Soul comes thus ſhipwracht
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:119879:7"/>Chriſt, thus tempeſtuous and forlorn, I know I need not inſiſt to prove; This I may call the ſtorming of a Soul, when Chriſt takes a Soul by his great power, ſuddenly breaks down all the ſtrong holds and high things, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5. This is uſually the way of an open ſinner, though not in the ſame height, neither in every open ſinner at his firſt converſion; But then ſometimes Jeſus Chriſt takes a Soul, as I may ſo ſpeak, upon eaſier terms, brings it in, <hi>leni afflatu,</hi> with a more gentle gale, yet ſo, that in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe of it there will be ſome ſhakings, ſomething of this tempeſt upon it, though the Soul hath a glimpſe of Chriſt, and his hand more ſenſibly ſupporting it; which I clear thus.</p>
               <p n="1">Firſt, If the ſeed of grace be ſown ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the heart (as ſometimes it is) that ſome Souls cannot remember the firſt work of it, yet if the Soul grow up to any meaſure of experience, it muſt be more ſhaken in order to its further ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing and purifying; It will meet with ſome kinde of tempeſts ordinarily, I ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſpake with any as to this Point, but more or leſſe did allow of it: But when the work of God is begun at ſome fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:119879:7"/>ripeneſſe of years, then certainly it ſhall meet with what I have ſet forth in ſome meaſure; Conſider, for a Soul to be awakened out of the deep ſleep of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſecurity, which ſin hath bound him in, To have Satan the ſtrong man diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt by a ſtronger then he, To have the guilt and filth of ſinne diſcovered by the holy Spirit, To have Chriſt deſtroy the works of Satan, the power and peace of corruptions that will ſet againſt him, with all the reaſonings of fleſh and bloud mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered up, To have, in a word, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, dead, earthy, dark, hard, proud, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſticall, unbeleeving heart of an obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate wretch, of death to become life, of darkneſſe, light; of a ſtone, fleſh; To have a grain of faith, break through all naturall impoſſibilities, ſpirituall wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, all diſcouragements within and without, when nothing within us to help forward beleeving, but every thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us (as I ſhall further ſhew:) Though all theſe be not enough to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Lord Jeſus, when he by his ſtrong arm will work, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.13. <hi>I will work, and who ſhall let it?</hi> yet certainly this work is not wrought forth in a dream (as we uſe to ſpeak of things inſenſibly done) not
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119879:8"/>without ſome ſhaking and concuſſion upon the ſpirit, ſomething of this tempeſt upon it, partly in the beginning, and partly in the progreſſe of converſion; <hi>Fides non fit ſine multo motu,</hi> ſaith <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cthon,</hi> faith is not wrought forth without much motion in the Soul; Yea, I might here ſhew into how many tempeſts from without and within, many a poor Soul (ſpecially ſuch whom God will moſt humble and fit for ſome ſpeciall ſervice) fals into, how many overwhelmings of ſpirit and guſts of temptations it is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently ſhaken with, but I intend to keep my ſelf chiefly to the diſcovery of the ſouls firſt approach to Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">It may yet be further enquired, What is the loweſt meaſure of ſuch conviction, in the bringing in of a Soul to Chriſt? In this there have been extreams, ſomtimes, I preſume, gracious men giving forth the tenour of their own converſion as a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall rule to all others; But in this caſe I may ſafely aſſert, that the firſt work of the Spirit is to <hi>convince of ſin,</hi> Joh. 16.7. And that ſuch a convincement that ſhall give a creature ſuch a ſight of ſin, that it muſt appear exceeding ſinfull, to be <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding ſin,</hi> Rom. 5.18. to be tyranni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119879:8"/>fin, filthy ſinne, condemning ſinne, which muſt not only flote in the head, but convince the conſcience, and affect the heart, that it muſt needs humble and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſe a creature as he goes out of himſelf and rowls upon Jeſus Chriſt; yea, he ſhall come in a periſhing condition, as I am to ſhew in the next Point; To deny ſuch preparations and qualifications (not ſuch I mean as of our ſelves but from the ſpirit) is to reaſon againſt the method of the Spirit witneſſed by Scripture and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; If the ſpirit of a ſinner be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally bound up in blindeneſſe, hardneſs of heart, inſenſibleneſſe, ſecurity, peace, then it will not make out for ſalvation by Chriſt, till the Spirit of God comes upon that blindeneſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo cauſeth the Soul to diſcern its own condition; and this, as the rebellions of our hearts begin to be ſubdued by that ſpirit, cauſeth a mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny, diſtemper, ſome kinde of tempeſt in the whole inward man, till the Spirit draweth vertue from Jeſus Chriſt more and more to work ſome meaſure of ſere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and compoſure upon it, as we are to ſhew in the cloſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Say ſome, This is a way to bring a Soul into bondage and tormenting fear,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:119879:9"/>No ſuch matter, 'Tis the way to bring him out of it: in order to the delivery from bondage, that bondage muſt be firſt diſcovered to and owned by the captive, which naturally he feels not, as above; To ſhew the captive his bondage, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his ſuing for deliverance, is the way for liberty, this clear <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. <hi>Ye have not received the ſpirit of bondage again to fear, but ye have received the ſpirit of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption,</hi> implying, <hi>ye are not now under the Law,</hi> and ſo in bondage again, as once you were, intimating they were ſo, and felt themſelves to be ſo, and that the Spirit did reveal it, and ſo brought them out of it, and wrought forth and witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Chriſt to them, whereby they cried Abba, Father,</p>
               <p n="4">4. How long is a Soul to lie in his bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage humbling himſelf? Till he caſt up an eye to Jeſus Chriſt to ſeek liberty in in him; Certainly, though a Soul is to renew his humblings under his bondage, ye not ſo to lie under it, but preſently to make in to Jeſus Chriſt to be freed from the guilt, condemnation, bondage, ſervice of ſin, pleading his own gracious pdrpoſes to him, as expreſſed, 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.8. 'twas his purpoſe to deſtroy the works
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:119879:9"/>of the devill, as I will purſue in the third point.</p>
               <p>And thus briefly I have opened what I here mean by this tempeſt in a poor ſoul, ſeeking Chriſt, and life, and peace in him, the way, and loweſt meaſure of it.</p>
               <p>If Jeſus Chriſt by his Word and Spirit doth thus awaken, enlighten, convince, raiſe ſome kinde of tempeſt in a poor ſoul, before it truly ſeeks out for life and peace in him; Let me in the firſt place ſpeak to the ſecure peacefull ſoul that perſwades it ſelf it hath hope enough for heaven, good intereſt enough in Jeſus Chriſt, and yet is not acquainted in any meaſure with ſuch workings of the ſpirit as this coming in with an awakning voice upon the naturall blindeneſſe and ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and bondage thou art bound up in. Let me tell thee, Soul, Better were the fierceſt tempeſt upon thy ſpirit then ſuch a calm: 'Tis ſitting with folded arms un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhadow of death; 'Tis ſinne in its power, bondage, peace upon thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the ſtrong man Satan keeping peace, that thou maieſt ſleep the ſleep of Death.</p>
               <p>But you will ſay, What, will you diſturb
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119879:10"/>the peace of my conſcience that I have enjoyed all the daies of my life?</p>
               <p>Ah Soul, miſerable peace, miſerable calm, none of Chriſts making; Spare me a little, let me then freely beſpeak thee; <hi>Awake thou that ſleepeſt and ariſe from the dead, and Chriſt ſhall give thee light,</hi> Eph. 5 Oh, awake from thy deadly calm and peace; <hi>Hear the voice of the Son of God and live,</hi> Joh. 5. Sinner, drowſie, care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, heartleſſe ſinner, that haſt been all thy life time ſubject to bondage, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.15. Hearken, conſider, ariſe, thy ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſafety, and peace, is the death of ſin upon thy ſoul: a captive in a dungeon of darkneſſe, and with fetters about thee, and ſeeſt it not! this is thy temper, thou haſt been at eaſe from thy youth and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led on thy lees, <hi>Jerem.</hi> 48.11. Thou haſt heard the firſt work of the ſpirit is to awake to Chriſt and Heaven, to hear the voice of God in thy Soul, ruſhing in upon thy ſinfull peace: So <hi>Adam</hi> Gen. 3. when after his ſinne he had thought to lie hid from God in peace covered with his fig-leaves, he heard the voice of the Lord God in the Garden, and then they were afraid, and further ſaw their own nakedneſſe; What voices
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119879:10"/>of God were they? <hi>Adam, where art thou? Haſt thou eaten of the Tree I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded thee not to eat of?</hi> To the Woman, <hi>What is this thou haſt done?</hi> v. 8, 9, 10. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So the Lord ſpeaks to a ſoul at firſt, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in an Ordinance, ſometimes in a ſudden voice out of it. Soul, where art thou? what is thy ſtate and condition as to eternity? what proviſion for heaven, if thy ſoul ſhould be now taken from thee? What is this thou haſt done ſo preſumptuouſly and peaceably to ſinne againſt thy God? to ſide with the devil and the world againſt the peace of thy own ſoul? What is this thou haſt done to neglect the care of a deſolate ſoul? what will it profit thee to gain the whole world and loſe thy own ſoul, and to be a caſtaway? a caſtaway from the holy, bleſſed, eternall reſt of God into the company of devils in endleſſe unredeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able torment: What Soul, what means thy eager purſuit of vanity, and ſo heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to the things of heaven and eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? With ſome ſuch voices God ſpeaks, and then the ſoul is made awake for hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and then it cries after God, confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, humbleth, bemoaneth, chargeth it ſelf, then the Lord directs that ſoul to
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119879:11"/>means ordinarily, whereby he will do it good, and reveal the way of life in Chriſt unto it, to deſtroy the power of ſin in it, and then though after back-ſlidings and much unſetledneſſe, and wavering, many reaſonings and temptations, as ſhewd, the ſoul ſettles in ſome good meaſure in the taſtings of the power and love of Chriſt in it, as I ſhall further ſhew; Oh that ſuch a voice or any of theſe might ſecretly glide in the ſoul of any poor creature that hath hitherto withſtood it, and might cauſe the deep thoughts of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity to ſeize upon thee: Let me rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon with thee, as in the counſel of God, to raiſe a tempeſt in ſtead of that peace, fear it not, for I will ſhew thee a Chriſt to calm all, to deſtroy ſin, to ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, to fill thy ſoul with joy and peace that ſhall never be taken away, never fear to paſſe through ſuch a tempeſt, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter go to harbour in a ſtorm, then periſh becalmed in the ſands. Why then, in thy moſt ſerious and retired thoughts be put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch Queſtions as I have mentioned to thy ſelf, if thou art moved and excited by theſe, and ſuch like: then this is the voice of God in them, if all that is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thee is ſtirred up to ſeek after Chriſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:119879:11"/>and our intereſt in him.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Then Conſider with thy ſelf what it is thy heart moſt earneſtly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſues, (if thou haſt not truly found and ſought Jeſus Chriſt, and life in him;) 'tis certainly to compaſſe ſome ſuch worldly deſign which may render thee eſteemed in the world without depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on other men, eſtimation with men, riches, pleaſures, to make up (as thou thinkeſt) a full contentment, theſe are the goodly pearls in the eyes of a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man, conſider then how empty and diſquieted thy ſpirit is left after ſuch a purſuit made good, and preſently the thoughts of ſome new one, or elſe thy ſpirit will languiſh in the former, and grow weary of it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Conſider the miſerable un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainty of all outward enjoyments, how liable to ſpoil, loſe, decay, <hi>Pro.</hi> 23. they taken from thee, or thou from them in a moment: Much might be ſaid to this.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, When thou haſt compaſſed all thy deſigns, ſo much earth thou canſt call thy own; thou muſt at laſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with juſt ſo much as will cover thy carkaſſe, a feaſt for worms. Now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare this with the ſalvation of a ſoul.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:119879:12"/>Firſt, What it is that is to be ſaved, A Soul, a precious darling Soul, a Soul worth more then the whole world, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.25. Conſider what a value God puts upon Souls, the whole could not be a ranſome for one Soul; had the whole Creation been in mans power, and he had offered it to God for the ſin of his ſoul, it had not been a valuable price; No, the bloud of the Son of God was the high price of Souls; Ah conſider the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſneſſe of a Soul, and it will awake thee.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Compare this with what the Soul is doing till 'tis enſafed in Chriſt, 'tis <hi>treaſuring up wrath till the day of wrath, and the revelation of the righteous judgement of God,</hi> as if not wrath enough in hell already, 'tis treaſuring up more; that wrath that made the holy Son of God cry out as 'twas poured upon him; the everlaſting weight of wrath of the juſt avenging God; all the judgements that ever thou heardſt or readſt of, are but as mercy to this; Now conſider with deep thoughts of heart, if all thy purſuits of outward enjoyments here, will poize ſalvation from ſuch, ſuch wrath.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Compare it, with what the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119879:12"/>full enjoyment of ſalvation is: and here we are ſwallowed up, the holy, bleſſed, full, eternall reſt of God, with a weight of glory, crowns of glory, transform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be made capable of enjoying it, where we ſhall never be tempted to ſin, nor ſin any more: Oh to be in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of Jeſus Chriſt, filled with the full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of love, continually ſatisfied, and yet never nauſeated, pleaſures, peace, reſt, joy, glory, God hlmſeif, whoſe preſence thou ſhalt as fully enjoy as a glorified creature can poſſibly be able!</p>
               <p>Now then I ſay, conſider, if the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch a precious Soul from ſuch unſupportable wrath to ſuch a fullneſſe of glory with the infinite God, be worth hazarding for diſquieting earthly acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modations, enjoyments, to cauſe thee ſo ſecurely to neglect ſuch ſalvation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3. where mark, 'tis not ſaid, the open ſcorning the means of ſuch ſalvation; but the neglecting of it.</p>
               <p>Yet a little further, Conſider 3. things as to this condition here below, that thou maiſt not think thy good is all in expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the leaſt of Jeſus Chriſt is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then all the world, ſhouldſt thou on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119879:13"/>ſuffer with Chriſt here, more glory in it then in all the world; <hi>The Spirit of God and of glory reſteth upon thee,</hi> 1 Peter 4.14. The reproach of Chriſt is better then the pleaſures of <hi>Pharaohs</hi> houſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. how better that ſweet and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly fellowſhip with him, thou maieſt here attain unto, that thou maiſt be able to ſay, Thou hadſt rather have one hour with Jeſus Chriſt, then all the treaſures of the world for ever; Ah, hadſt thou one taſte of his love, how wouldeſt thou thirſt after him, though this be as a riddle to a dark carnall heart that knows and ſavors him not.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider, That all theſe reſtleſſe deſires, affections, and windings of thy heart, ſhall. be raiſed and refined, and meet with that abundant ſatisfaction in Jeſus Chriſt, far above what thou canſt propoſe to thy ſelf in the purſuits of things here below, ſolid and durable ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentment, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.18. though with ſome diſturbances by reaſon of diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers from ſinfull fleſh, yet 'tis here, The more of Chriſt, the more compoſure of ſpirit, ſweetneſſe, reſt; which is not ſo in the more gain of earthly advantages, theſe do only widen and enlarge, but not ſatisfie deſires.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:119879:13"/>3. Conſider, that with Jeſus Chriſt thou haſt the promiſe of all other things beſt for thee, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. what wouldeſt thou have more, unleſſe thou wouldſt be thy own carver in the world, and not take in the wiſedom of God to diſpoſe them to thee? Say, Men of the world, they would make as ſure proviſion as they may for themſelves and families, and ſo contrive, deſign, eat the bread of care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe; but let thy purchaſe, gain, and intereſt thou aimeſt at, be thy part in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, Count but all things loſſe to win Chriſt, and then thou gaineſt right to all things, and ſo if thou wanteſt any outward mercy, 'tis not becauſe God thinketh it too good for thee, but not ſo fit for thee; God ſeeth that mercy would haply leſſen thee in the ſweeter cloſer en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments of Jeſus Chriſt; why then, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, if that be the reaſon why the Lord withholds ſuch and ſuch things from thee thou wilt conſider now I have more of Jeſus Chriſt for it, and ſo no looſer by the hand, no need of repining of ſpirit in me, but to want them chearfully and gladly; yea, this will be thy bleſſedneſſe, that whereas now thou canſt not miſſe ſuch or ſuch things, but thy heart ſinks
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119879:14"/>within thee, then thou wilt know how to anſwer all thy cares of ſpirit, and ſee the wiſe hand of God ordering all for thy good; So that here's the way to provide all, to unſafe all, to ſweeten all, to have part in Jeſus Chriſt, to be earneſt in the purſuit of him, till he will ſay unto thy ſoul, I am thine, and a Covenant paſſed between thee and him, and he is fairer then the children of men, and all beauty and goodneſſe in him, then, whereas o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, have meer creatures, thou haſt the love and goodneſs of God in them, thou haſt the not by common providence, but by a covenant of love, by Jeſus Chriſt, by promiſe, the leaſt mercy is ſweet unto thee, for the kindeneſſe of God is in it.</p>
               <p>Take then theſe three together, the leaſt of Chriſt better then all the world, all enjoyments which are promiſed in the creatures eminently in him, with him the promiſe of all other things; What can thy ſpirit be opened to more? O wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed principle of Atheiſm and unbelief! what hath ſinne and devils done upon a poor worm, that he ſhould in the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, deadneſſe, emptineſſe, diſquietneſs of the creatures be ſeeking light, life, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, contentment, which they are not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:119879:14"/>able in the leaſt meaſure to give, and one drop of Jeſus Chriſt and Grace brings them all as fountain'd up in him.</p>
               <p>One word more, and (I truſt) thou ſhalt ſay thou art inexcuſable, O man! <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1.</p>
               <p>If theſe things be ſo, and there it thus but one choice in the world that can qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et the reſtleſſe ſpirit of man, the choſen one of God, in whom his ſoul delighteth for ever, why do we lie doting and puz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling our ſelves in darkneſſe, and diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves in vain, why do we not break off theſe Idols from our hearts, and call them in, and ſet them to Jeſus Chriſt? Oh let my ſoul chooſe him, let him be the dear, dear choice of my ſoul, give me him or I die!</p>
               <p n="2">2. If he be the choſen of God, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of his ſoul, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.1. the heart of the infinite incomprehenſible God can be delighted, ſatisfied, filled, from and to all eternity, with and by him, well-plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and never weary of him; Shall not the finite ſpirit of a poor creature be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome with the ocean of his goodneſſe that is in him? ſhall it be afraid and ſtand reaſoning, whether it ſhall have earth or him? Oh the folly of the ſons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119879:15"/>of men, to hear of ſuch a prize, ſuch an Indies of all ſweetneſſe and treaſure, and but a ſhort time to venture for him; (looſe him now, and give a thouſand worlds for him hereafter, and now gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a look from him) (though now his bowels more yearn, and his heart beats and pants after ſouls with more fervency then all the creatures deſires can make in one) yet that wretched creatures enſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to a curſed peace, kept by Satan, ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lizing empty nothings, fullfilling luſts that reſtleſly hurry them up and down, ſhould have lower, baſer thoughts of Chriſt then of the baſeſt thing they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy; for they will not miſſe one of them to gain him; the pooreſt meaneſt thing they enjoy hath more of their heart, more care and thoughts of their ſpirits toward it, then Jeſus Chriſt hath. Conſider thy own heartleſneſſe how ſeldome thou art in the thought of Jeſus Chriſt, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life in him; how ſeldome the deep ſenſe of ſalvation in him is upon thee; and this 'tis, thou muſt needs ſay, 'tis thus with me, wretch that I am! what do I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow the ſtrength of my ſpirit upon? why then poor creature as thou art, what ſhouldſt thou do but like that wiſe Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119879:15"/>man <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. who having found one pearl of great price, he went and ſold all that he had, and bought it; Ah ſuch a pearl the pearl of God, the pearl of heaven and earth, the pearl of ſouls, 'tis ſweeteſt Jeſus Chriſt, whatever is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious is laid up in him: Now then, ſell all that thou haſt, how ſo? that is, be contented to venture the loſſe of all for Chriſt, and thou gaineſt enſureſt all, as ſhewd, yet all thy riches, pleaſures, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments under thy feet for Chriſt, let all, all, and ten thouſand times more go, ſo thou haſt Chriſt; Ay, but how ſhall I buy him? Will gold and ſilver do it? The meaning is, to gain him, 'tis ſpoken comparatively, As Merchant men will ſell all to buy a pearl of ineſtimable price; ſo will poor ſouls that truly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve theſe things to be in Jeſus Chriſt as the holy Spirit of God, and the experiences of his own witneſſe to be in him, divorce their hearts from all, venture all to winne, to winne Jeſns Chriſt. But muſt I then caſt off all, my calling, all my poſſeſſions? No, but ſubject them to the purſuit of Jeſus Chriſt, get them looſened from thy heart, let it not be a weight upon thee to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119879:16"/>thy ſoul from ſoaring after him, keep them but as under-things, things thou muſt have or be without, and not be the leſſe bleſſed, and ſo in obedience to God and ſubmiſſion to his good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, be induſtrious in thy calling: but the motions, ſtrength, aims of thy ſpirit, to win and enjoy, love and honour Jeſus Chriſt, and ſuch will the Father honour, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. No loſſe of time to ſeek him in his word, no ſelf-deniall for him, no motion or good word for Chriſt in ſincerity, no witneſſe for his Kingdom, Goſpel, Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but the Father treaſureth it up, and will put honour upon thee for it.</p>
               <p>And now having thus a little dwelt upon this, to take off all Objections from thy enſnared heart; Be not afraid to be awakened, and deeply conſidering the ſtate of thy poor ſoul, though diſtempers and diſquietneſſe ariſe, though it be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtuous with thee for a time, ſee the bleſſed and glorious recompences of it, by the Lord of life and glory here and to all eternity; Aud now I will conclude thee as ſtupid as a worm groveling in the earth, as thou doſt, if theſe ſo weighty and important conſiderations doe not upon thee, being ſuch as Jeſus Chriſt left
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119879:16"/>to move and pierce the Rocks of mens hearts, to leade them to life in himſelf, and ſuch as if thou putſt them off, will be as Swords in thy bones, will flaſh back upon thee as a thouſand Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againſt thee, if thou receive them not into thy heart, if thou receive them not into thy heart, as thou wouldeſt do things that are moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to thee; Why doth Chriſt ſo often knock and thou wilt not own him? thou art gone abroad or aſleep: In a word then, either put in thy plea to God, or ſubmit and own it, that 'tis better to paſſe through a ſmall tempeſt to Jeſus Chriſt, then to enjoy a world of empty contentments here, and be a caſtaway, under the furious tempeſts of Gods wrath for ever and ever: Ah Soul, once get hold on the skirts of Jeſus Chriſt, and he will anchor thee to a ſafe harbour; windes and waves, ſin, conſcience, fears, unbelief; Satan, all obey him; A word from him quiets all; Be not like great debtors, afraid to enter into the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thy debts, thy ſinfull eſtate for fear of diſquietneſſe (that is, to reſiſt the ſtrivings of God with thee, and he will not ſtrive alwaies) but ſet the ſins
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119879:17"/>of heart and life before thee, though they ſwell to a numberleſſe ſumme in bloudy characters, I am yet to ſhew thee Jeſus Chriſt the beſt and ſafeſt pay-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the world. But thou wilt ſay, What is that to thee? ſpread them before God and ſeek him to ſue all thy Bonds and Debts upon Jeſus Chriſt, and God will take him thy Surety, 'twas the good plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Jeſus Chriſt to cancell and kill them all, they did their worſt upon him, ſo get to him, and in him, and the worſt is over, and all the bleſſedneſſe I have pointed at is thine, but I ſhall prevent my ſelf: Theſe I have laid down as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wakening, exciting conſiderations to a poor ſoul, to whom the experiences of theſe things are yet but dark, and ſo the Lord bleſſe them to thy ſoul, and I paſſe to the next thing.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Saith a poor ſoul, Well, I have had ſome good thoughts Chriſt-ward, and have made reſignment of my ſelf unto him, but I fear I am too much aſleep as yet; That may be; Therefore be more awakened, look back to the ſins thy ſoul hath been divorced from, but not ſo, as to looſen the preſent hold thou haſt on Chriſt, but to humble and abaſe thee
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:119879:17"/>more, and ſo cauſe thee to purſue and prize him more: Haply thou art a ſoul whom Jeſus Chriſt takes more gently to himſelf by degrees, with a ſofter hand, and ſo the tempeſt not ſo great: But if the leaſt of him be better then the beſt of all the world to thee, a Covenant with him, He is a choſen one and pearl to thee, yea, if it be thy daily mourning he is no more a pearl unto thee, no more precious, thy heart ſo dull, and then thou calleſt to him to come and make a more powerfull and fuller abode in thy ſoul, then be ſure he is thine, though a trembling jealouſie upon thee to the contrary. Now if the Lord in much mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy hath awakened thee by this or any other voice, or more awakened thee then thou waſt, I would ſtill keep thee company in this diſcourſe till thou findeſt in Jeſus Chriſt what I have here propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to thee; And ſo to ſhew thee yet fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the dealings of Chriſt to thee, as thou comeſt as a way-faring ſoul to him, in the next propoſition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="observation">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 2.</note>
                  <hi>When a Soul comes ſavingly, it comes in a periſhing condition to Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Lord ſave us we periſh; <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, we are loſt, or are in a loſt condition; loſt, do
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119879:18"/>thou ſave us; This doth rightly anſwer to the heart of Chriſt, and his purpoſe revealed in the Goſpel, <hi>I am come to ſeek and to ſave,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that which was loſt or ready to periſh; that really is ſo, and that ſhall ſee it ſelf to be ſo, <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.10. So in that threefold Parable <hi>Luk.</hi> 15. to ſet forth ſuch a ſinner that Chriſt draws in to his ſalvation, <hi>I have found my Sheep which was loſt,</hi> ver. 6. <hi>Rejoyce with me, I have found the piece that was loſt,</hi> verſ. 9. And ſo of the Prodigall, <hi>Let us eat and rejoyce, my Son was loſt and is found,</hi> ver. 23, 24. 'Tis Chriſt's rejoycing to finde ſinners loſt in themſelves; To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>Paul,</hi> Phil. 3.9. <hi>That I may be found in Christ,</hi> implying, he was loſt in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; Now to open this, how a ſoul is ſaid to come to Chriſt in this loſt and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing condition.</p>
               <p n="1">Firſt, Periſhing in ſinne, ſuch a ſight of ſin as before is deſcribed, if it ſtay in its ſinne, it muſt certainly periſh; Sinne cannot enſafe; The leaſt ſinne is able to damn, much more the multitudes of them that lie undiſcharged upon it.</p>
               <p n="2">Secondly, A Soul that comes truly to Chriſt, comes periſhing in its own ſtrength; 'Tis likely, thoſe who were
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119879:18"/>ready to periſh in the Ship with Chriſt in the tempeſt, that they toiled long in their own ſtrength, rowed with their own oars, with much painfulneſle, till they ſaw all was in vain, and then they throw down all, <hi>Maſter ſave, or we periſh;</hi> So a poor creature after ſome conviction and awakening, 'tis apt at firſt to be toyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in its own ſtrength, its own naturall ſufficiencies, ſets to repentance, duties, obedience, in its own ſtrength, turns in the outward man from the groſſer evils of his waies, but then backſlides again, and all becauſe he would be his own deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer, work for and by himſelf, at leaſt contribute ſomething himſelf; But to come weak and ſtrengthleſſe to Jeſus Chriſt, helpleſſe in it ſelf, this goes hard, To acknowledge to the glory of God and our own ſhame; That if any thing be left on our ſcore, to make good with God, periſh we muſt, this goes to the quick; indeed our pride and ſelf-love is very unwilling to yeeld to this, a crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture would not be found to be at ſuch a totall loſſe with God, ſo farre to have ſpoiled and undone himſelf; to be ſo wholly weakened and deadned by ſin, as not to be able to help the Lord Jeſus one
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119879:19"/>little in ſaving us, but the whole ſtreſſe muſt be laid upon him: yet thus it is, <hi>when we were without ſtrength Chriſt died,</hi> Rom. 5.6. And ſo when Chriſt comes to give a ſoul the bleſſing of his death, and to eſtate him in it; It cauſeth the ſoul to know and feel that it is without ſtrength, and helpleſſe, and then 'twill be at his feet periſhing in it ſelf without him; No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more ſtrongly ſetled upon the ſpirit of a ſinner then this ſelf-ſufficiency, and opinion of its own power; He can pray, repent, hear the Word, receive, be juſt, do all, and acceptably enough to God, as he deemeth, and ſtill on the lees of his own ſtrength, not knowing what belongs to the ſpirituall performance of any duty, and ſo befools himſelf; Now this is the firſt thing a ſoul coming into Chriſt, is to periſh in, in all its own ſtrength.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It is to periſh in all its own righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; 'Twas in vain for theſe poor men in the Ship, to be hiding themſelves In cabins of their own, when the Ship was ſo toſſed and ſhaken; to lie nuzling in their own wares, though never ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious; No, all the precious merchandiſe muſt over-board, paſſe for nothing; So when a ſoul comes to Chriſt for help, all
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119879:19"/>its own cabins of its own righteouſneſſe muſt be caſt away; All thy former ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of hearing, praying, being juſt and ſober (if thou werſt ſo) which was thy cabin, thy covert in the room of Chriſt, muſt be lookt upon as thy ſins, as that which is but an abomination in the pure eyes of God, <hi>Pro.</hi> 15.8. <hi>The prayer of the wicked</hi> (that is, of every perſon out of Chriſt) <hi>is an abomination to the Lord;</hi> As for thy publique worſhip that haply thou repoſeſt moſt in, What ſaith the Spirit of God of it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.13. <hi>vain oblati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, abomination, it is iniquity, the ſolemn meeting, they are a trouble to me, I am wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to bear them,</hi> And as for private prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, plainly ſaith he, <hi>When you make them, I will not hear them,</hi> v. 15. And why? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſins of ſuch a perſon are not pardoned, his perſon not juſtified, he is not in Chriſt, he doth not ſanctifie Gods Name in his ſervices, not direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to right ends, and ſo hatefull to the pure and righteous God; And yet fond man is apt to hide and ſecure himſelf in theſe things, as <hi>Adam</hi> in his fig-leaves; So he prays a little, in a cuſtomary dead-hearted manner, with ſome kinde of outward reverence: ſo he gives alms, goes
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119879:20"/>to publique worſhip, is righteous to men: (things good in themſelves, if aright, and to right ends performed;) And if he ſlip, a little repentance of his own added, and Chriſt to make up what he wants, this is the hold of the moſt, and ſends as many ſouls away empty from Chriſt, as any thing whatſoever; What formall profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, I mean, the common bulk of the people of this Nation, reach ſo far as a Phariſee in all the duties they boaſted in? And yet obſerve and do it with deep thoughts of heart, that in <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. when the Lord Jeſus preacht his laſt Sermon to them, after he hath ſeven times pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced woes unto them, he puts this confounding queſtion to them, <hi>Ye Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Vipers, how ſhall you eſcape the damnation of hell?</hi> ver. 33. Moſt (indeed) periſh within the pale of the Church up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account. That in <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.3. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many others is very remarkable, They being ignorant of Gods righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, go about to eſtabliſh their own righteouſneſſe, and have not ſubmitted to the righteouſneſſe of God; 1. Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, how holy and perfect that righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe is, in which God will accept of and juſtifie a creature; Ignorant of the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119879:20"/>righteouſneſſe of the Law, conſidering not that the holy and ſpirituall Law of God reacheth to the heart and ſpirit, and that one motion awry, if we ſtand to that, damns a ſoul for ever, or that the worth of his repentance and duties can make God amends for what he fails, as ſhew'd; and ignorant of the full and acceptable righteouſneſſe of Chriſt (though per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſome generall notion of it in the brain, and able to diſcourſe of it, yet as to ſound and ſpirituall diſcerning of it, and cloſing with it, ignorant of it) and ſo goeth about to eſtabliſh his own righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe; And ſo is eſtabliſhing that which the Lord will deſtroy, eſtabliſhing that which he ſhould be periſhing in, and ſo doth not ſubmit to the righteouſneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt; through ignorance and pride, and ſelf-conceit, doth not ſubmit unto it, never beaten out of and periſhed in their own, that they might ſubmit unto Chriſt, to be accepted for Chriſts obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and not for their own; And yet having thus ſubmitted, to delight in all the holy will of God alſo,</p>
               <p n="3">3. A ſoul muſt periſh as to any ſupport in its priviledges, of being baptized, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, of the true Church, and the like,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119879:21"/>being no Papiſt, no Heretick, nor Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick, as people are wont to boaſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; Though theſe are priviledges, yet to build a ſafe condition upon them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt and regeneration, is a moſt dangerous ſin.</p>
               <p n="4">4. A ſoul muſt periſh in all its outward comforts, as to be a refuge for him, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hath been ſaid as to this already: The ſpirit of a man being an active mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver muſt faſten and feed upon ſomething, and having loſt God and communion with him, it turns to the creatures, and would ſatisfie it ſelf upon them, which bearing no proportion to it, cannot af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford him fulneſſe; Therefore convinced of this, it is reſolved to throw them off, and ſeeing them altogether inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to cover him from the wrath of God, to appeaſe the conſcience, to give one dram of bleſſing to his ſoul, he comes to Chriſt, as having reſted (ſuch a reſt as it was) in periſhing things, and ſees if he ſtaies upon them, he muſt periſh in them.</p>
               <p>In a word, Conſider all thoſe lying Refuges, which a ſoul findes out to hide himſelf and pacifie conſcience with, there doth the ſearching God finde him our, and drive him out of them, and unfaſtens
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119879:21"/>his hold of them, then doth God as it were throw him at the feet of Chriſt, then Chriſts bowels yern after him, and laies hold upon him; Then will that ſoul tell the Lord Jeſus that he is come to periſh in his view, under his eye, if he do periſh, but reſolved to look after no other help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, if his good pleaſure be not towards him; I will yet ſtep aſide to ſpeak to a ſoul, that hath not yet thus periſhed in all but Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Why then ſinner Conſider, here's that will take down thy plumes, thy im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred ſelf-conceit and ſelf-flatteries that will undoe thee, if thou any longer hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneſt to them; and yet walks up and down as ſelf-conceitedly, as if all thou truſteſt in were as ſafe as heaven.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As to thy ſin; I have pleaded with thee before, but a word more, Dareſt thou pretend to be ſafe in thy ſin an hour more? Dareſt thou walk upon the brink of hell, and ſmile upon it? Tell me, Doſt thou beleeve ſinne as certainly damnable (while thou art in it, unpardoned, not fled to Jeſus Chriſt) as God reigneth in the heaven and is juſt? Doſt thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it? ſure thou doſt not; elſe thou doſt not give reſt unto thy ſpirit till thou haſt
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119879:22"/>found a Saviour to take thy ſin away, and his Spirit witneſſing the ſame effectually unto thee: Oh then, come and be as thou art (and be not too proud to own it) a periſhing ſinner at Chriſts feet; How poor and trembling will a periſhing man be, that lies wholly at the mercy of another? So is it with thee, thou haſt not ſo much as bread for thy ſoul till thou comeſt periſhing and hungring after Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As to thy own ſtrength a word more; If it be ſo, that thou art ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, helpleſſe in thy ſelf, not able to move one ſtep towards God ſavingly of thy ſelf, thy heart as dead and weak as water; how poor a creature may this make thee in thy own eyes? Is it likely that what thou haſt done hitherto, and performed toward God hath been in thy own naturall ſtrength, and ſo not accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? oh then go and pleade with God to give thee a heart, even upon his own free promiſe, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. <hi>I will give them a heart to know me;</hi> Helpleſſe ſinner what wouldſt thou have more? Haſt thou not a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual heart? I will give it, ſaith God, and give it for humble asking; Oh art thou willing to turn at Gods reproof; then <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold,
<pb facs="tcp:119879:22"/>I will powr out my ſpirit upon you;</hi> Behold, take notice of it, as the moſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging promiſe thou canſt fly unto; Turn thy face to Chriſt, and hear what he will ſpeak, even upon thoſe unanſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able arguments he laies down in his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, yea, beſeech him but to turn thee to him, and himſelf to thee, and he will do it; O then go preſently to him, while thou ſeeſt the way open, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly beg his Spirit, and pleade Chriſts own promiſe: And that ſpirit ſhall be an humbling, ſubduing, praying, renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, quickning, mortifying, guiding, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forting Spirit in thee; And ſo thou ſhalt learn to perform all in the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As to thy own righteouſneſſe let me have one word more with thee; Know, that though thou maiſt make a good eſtimate of thy ſelf, and that others do ſo alſo, in the things thou doſt towards God and man, yet Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that <hi>what is highly eſteemed among men is an abomination to the Lord,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15. To be round with thee, Dareſt thou imagine to ſtand and appear before the infinitely righteous, holy, heart-ſearching God, in ſuch a patcht
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:119879:23"/>up defiled covering, as thy own doings and performances make? Wilt thou lie down wrapt in a cobweb (ſuch is thy hope in this, <hi>Job.</hi> 8.13.) to cover thee from the piercing ſtorms of God, or to hide a heart full of iniquity and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eriſie from the eye of God? or doſt thou think that Jeſus Chriſt will joyn righteouſneſſe with thine? In a word, in ſtead of being a well-conceited Phariſee (for 'tis uo better) Go and be a poor ſinner at Chriſts feet, and be willing to let him have all the glory in thy ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; Even put on Jeſus Chriſt by an humble, free, totall reſignment of thy ſelf unto him, to undertake thy cauſe, as hath been ſhewd, to work all thy works for thee and in thee; And in ſtead of thy own defiled righteouſneſſe, thou haſt ſtood a tip-toe in, the entire obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Chriſt ſhall be thine, and thou ſhalt appear before God in that full, pure, ſpotleſſe, acceptable righteouſneſs of the Son of his, in which the ſoul of God is infinitely delighted; Ah Soul, what a change is this, to part with filth and abomination, for the glorious righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of the Son of God, to be clad in it, and even ſhine forth before God in it.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:119879:23"/>4. Well, do the ſame as to any conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in all thy Church-priviledges, of being baptized, being a Proteſtant, no heretick; Do the ſame as to all creature-refuges, as hath been ſhewed; and being undone and ſhattered in them, do not dare to be ſafe in them any longer, no, no pretenſion to ſafety, till thou ſhalt be ſafe in the Lord Jeſus, by a clear and full cloſure with him, till thou haſt him in thy arms by faith, thy ſoul embracing and twining it ſelf about him, till he ſhall ſay unto thee, I am thine, and thou ſhalt finde power and vertue coming from him.</p>
               <p>From what hath been ſaid maiſt thou now with deep thoughts of heart ſay thus within thy ſelf; Ah wretch that I have been, fond, ſelf-pleaſing, ſelf-flattering wretch; how well conceited of my ſelf, how able thought I my ſelf to do every thing, how confidently have I ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the perfect God in the performance of my carnall duties, when they were as filthy as ſin could make them, and God was loathing of them? Now I ſee one Jeſus Chriſt is ten thouſand times better then them all; Now I will caſt anchor into him, now I will contend for him as
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:119879:24"/>for life; Now I will enquire, ſeek, wait upon his voice (his ſpirit enabling me) till I ſhall finde him, and all thoſe Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings are reported to be in him; Now I will be diligent in duties upon a better account, not as they are able to render me accepted and juſtified before God (ſo I do and ever will renounce them) but as means (bleſſed be God) to conveigh Chriſt to my ſoul, and as the teſtimony of my obedience to him.</p>
               <p>And now, if by the Lords bleſſing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee what hath been ſaid, or thou waſt ſuch before, even a more periſhing ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in thy own eyes, take yet what far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is implied in the heart of theſe words, <hi>Lord ſave, I periſh,</hi> which may be enlarged in ſuch a plea as this; Oh bleſſed Lord Jeſus of Life and Glory, Here's a ſoul at thy feet with the weight of numberleſſe ſins upon it, but not one dram of righteouſneſſe to cover him; a deſolate, forlorn, ſhipwrackt worm, that ſtands bound over in thouſands of debts to the juſt and dreadfull God of heaven and earth; But hath not ſo much as one mite to pay him, unleſſe with the forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of my immortall ſoul; Here I come with thee, as thou haſt commanded, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119879:24"/>throw my ſelf upon thee; He venture an immortall ſoul with thee, If thou haſt not treaſures enough to ſpare lying by thee, the infinite merits of thy own bloud, If thou wilt not freely ſatisfie for me, and take the debts of my ſins upon thee, and ſo ſtand between a juſt God and a condemned ſinner; If thou haſt not favour enough with the righteous God to prevail for me; Oh I muſt periſh, everlaſtingly periſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lord</hi>] It implies thou art mighty and able to do it, for all power is committed to thee; If there be not power enough with thee, thou who art the mighty God, the Prince of Peace, and ſo able to reſcue my darling ſoul, I am contented to ſink before thee; but thou, thou alone art the Lord of Life; oh magnifie thy great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er upon me, and even be my Lord, my Lord, other Lords beſide thee I would have none, <hi>Lord ſave,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Save,</hi>] 'Tis for a great and weighty matter that I pleade, that I come unto thee for, No leſſe then to be eternally ſaved, ſaved from the everlaſting wrath and vengeance of God, ſaved to ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life and glory in the glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God for evermore; O thou Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119879:25"/>of men (that's thy Name and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Title) didſt thou not paſſe through many abaſements, when thou waſt upon earth, very unſuitable to thy glorious perſon? didſt thou not drink of a moſt bitter cup, full of the wrath of divine juſtice? And was not this then in thy heart, did not this then bear thee up, that thou ſhouldeſt ſave? ah ſave poor helpleſſe ſouls, that could never have been ſaved without thee; Oh, hadſt thou not infinitely delighted in ſaving loſt ſouls, thou hadſt never been at ſo much pains and travell and coſt in the work; Oh therefore <hi>Save, Lord Save;</hi> Yea, <hi>Save,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I periſh;</hi>] Muſt, will periſh, If thou doſt not ſave; <hi>Save,</hi> for the waters are come over my ſoul, I am ſinking with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out thee; <hi>Maſter, Maſter, I periſh</hi> Luk. 8. <hi>Maſter, Careſt thou not that I periſh?</hi> Mar. 4. Oh let it never be told in <hi>Gath,</hi> that even a complaining, forlorn ſoul periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at thy feet; What, at the feet of a Jeſus? Alas, if thou careſt not that I pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, who will? If thou pitieſt not, who will or can? Oh for the honour of thy own Name pity; If I ſhould now periſh in the view of harbour, now I have ſeen and cried to a Saviour, Thy enemies will
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119879:25"/>ſpeak evil of thy Name; Well, bleſſed Lord, thou ſeeſt all the arguments I have to move thee; That which I will ſtick upon and never give thee over with is, that I muſt periſh, periſh without thee, yea, periſh in thy ſight, if thou ſuccour me not; <hi>Lord ſave, I periſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well now, Soul, If thou doſt in this or the like manner pant after Jeſus Chriſt in ſuch a periſhing poſture, and thine eyes are upon him, and followeſt him, and waiteſt what he will ſpeak unto thee, I will a little prevent thee, and ſhew thee a copy or two of his tender heart in this particular: See <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.10. <hi>For the Son of man is come to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt;</hi> He <hi>came,</hi> 'twas his errand, his buſineſſe, 'twas the main thing he had in his heart: What? that which thou ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly look'ſt for, even to <hi>ſave,</hi> yea more, to <hi>ſeek</hi> whom he might ſave; but what kinde of perſons? even ſuch as thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteſt thy ſelf unto him, that which is loſt, ſouls that come as loſt and periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in themſelves to ſeek him; Have the worſt thoughts of thy ſelf, it can reach but to be a loſt ſoul, and ſuch, (ſaith Chriſt) if he be worthy of credit with thee he came to ſeek; If thou art ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119879:26"/>him, why, he was ſeeking thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; He left it upon record in his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and he is in heaven to ſee it made good; So much will that Scripture af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford thee, and beleeve it: Another <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.22. <hi>Look unto me, and be ye ſaved;</hi> Well now, doſt thou <hi>look up</hi> with a long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing expectation to Jeſus Chriſt for ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to hear what he will ſpeak unto thee? why now, ſaith Chriſt to ſuch a looking expecting ſoul, <hi>Be ye ſaved,</hi> Be it unto you as you will; To confirm it to thee, hear him further in the ſame Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, <hi>I am God, and none elſe,</hi> None but me is able: and as for his good will and faithfullneſſe in performing it, he fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, <hi>I have ſworn by my ſelf, the word is gone out of my mouth in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> And then obſerve, <hi>ver.</hi> 24. what he aſſures thee of, how fully he anſwers thy errand, <hi>Surely ſhall one ſay, In the Lord have I righteouſneſſe and ſtrength;</hi> Mark, while thou art ſeeking and looking for it, thou haſt it, while thou art periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in thy own, thou haſt found it fully in Jeſus Chriſt; And therefore, as it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows there, In the Lord thou ſhalt be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified and glorified. Yea more (ſaith Chriſt) that thou maieſt not think it a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119879:26"/>common matter to him, as if he did not care, or it did not much concern him; <hi>Rejoyce with me,</hi> ſaith he in <hi>Luke,</hi> as ſhewed, <hi>for I have found that which was loſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But yet there remains one Objection in thy heart, that as yet thou doſt not taſte the comfort of this, thou doſt not yet ſo powerfully hear the voice of Chriſt, nor ſo comfortably ſee his face; The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of this are to be cleared in the next point.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="observation">
               <p>
                  <hi>Jeſus Chriſt for a time ſeems to take no notice of a tempeſtuous periſhing ſoul, though nigh unto it.</hi>—But he was aſleep.</p>
               <p>Now this ſeems not conſiſtent with all thoſe gracious and melting invitations of Chriſt, of poor wearied ſouls to come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, that beſpeak the yearnings and pantings of his bowels towards them; but yet ſee how conſiſtent it will be.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That 'tis his uſuall way of dealing, See <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.22. The poor woman there cried after Chriſt for mercy to her daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but it holds, and is ſo applied in ſpirituall mercies alſo, for ſhe came in ſaving faith; The Lord at firſt anſwers not a word, as if he were careleſſe of her, as if it had been no part of his bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:119879:27"/>in the world to take notice of poor ſinners at his feet; and when he did anſwer (for ſhe would not from him without her errand) his words were full of diſcouragement, <hi>Send her away,</hi> ſay the Diſciples, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. I am not come but to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> (yet ſtill ſhe worſhiped him, Lord help me,) And yet a more reſerved Reply, <hi>It is not meet to caſt the Childrens bread to dogs;</hi> Yet ſtill ſhe preſſed, and had her errand, though Chriſt ſeem'd thus to chide her: So with <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalene,</hi> Joh. 26.11. <hi>Mary</hi> was ſeeking Chriſt alone, and ſeeking him in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per notion, a crucified Chriſt, and ſhe ſought him in a ſweet poſture, weeping after him, reſtleſſe till ſhe found him; Now, Chriſt ſeemed for a time to take no notice of her, though he were ſtanding by her, and his heart full of love to her; See the Spouſe <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1,2. <hi>I ſought him but I found him not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>There are many choice Reaſons of the Lords dealing thus with a ſoul for a time.</p>
               <p n="1">1. This works for the heightning and drawing forth of faith; for a ſoul to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after Chriſt when the tempeſt is upon it, in a periſhing condition, and Chriſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:119879:27"/>ſeems to take no notice of it; When his preſent dealings ſeem to thwart with his Invitations and promiſes, this heightens faith, as in the woman of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and draws it forth to purſue Chriſt the more.</p>
               <p n="2">2. When Jeſus Chriſt thus withholds his ſmiles and comfort for a time, he is preparing the heart to be a fit place for him, to break the pride and ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our hearts, to ſubdue the rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of them, to make crooked things ſtraight, and then when our ſpirits are thus ſubdued and broken, there's no more but for Chriſt to come in and dwell with us, when our hearts are thus pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to receive him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He for a time thus clouds himſelf, ſeems to take no notice of a poor ſoul, that the' ſoul may the more experimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally ſee, that all other refuges cannot quiet the tempeſt upon it; A ſoul will be apt to be making trial in ſuch a caſe of creatures, and fly from one created con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment to another, and to try what they are able to afford in ſuch an hour; And when the ſoul can finde quietneſſe in none, but ſtill reſtleſſe (as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſhew'd it will be) Then it will
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:119879:28"/>cloſely and ſtrongly cleave to Chriſt, Then it will clearly ſee (when Chriſt ſpeaks) that all its quietneſſe, comfort, peace, was from Jeſus Chriſt alone.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It makes for the honour of the Lord Jeſus, for a poor creature to continue ſeeking and panting after him, and will not off, even when Chriſt hides his face from it; This gives more honour to Chriſt then to live upon him, when he ſweetly reveals himſelf to a ſoul: 'Tis an honour to a friend to truſt him when abſent from him, yea, when he ſeems to frown; ſo for a poor ſoul to follow and beleeve Jeſus Chriſt ſweet, and gracious, and faithfull, though it never taſted him, gives moſt glory unto him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. When Chriſt thus withholds himſelf for a time, it makes his preſence the more welcome when he comes; The Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus loves to come welcome to a ſoul; And how welcome is he? what a heaven is his appearance to a poor, tempeſtuous, clou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, periſhing ſoul? When we have loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for a dear frieud till we are ready to give off expectation, and then he comes ſuddenly upon us with ſmiles and kindeneſſe, what a joy is it? So when the poor friends of Chriſt who lay hold on
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:119879:28"/>the Covenant of his peace, and cry after him, Ah, when Lord, when? And then he comes with a ſudden ſmiling voice, Why <hi>Soul, I am thine,</hi> and I have betro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed thee unto me, yea, but one word, as to <hi>Mary Magdalene, Mary,</hi> and ſhe anſwers <hi>Rabboni,</hi> oh my Maſter; This reaſon may be further illuſtrated in the caſe of <hi>Joſeph</hi> and his Brethren, <hi>Gen.</hi> 44. When they came to him as diſtreſſed men, <hi>Joſeph</hi> reſerves himſelf for a time, did not make known himſelf, though his heart were full of yearnings after them, and what was it for but to make way for the greater endearments of them unto him? So much unexpected love let out upon them, that it even brake their hearts, <hi>for they were troubled at his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> ſaith that Scripture, being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come with the loving-kindeneſs he ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them: whether <hi>Joſeph</hi> were in this a type of Chriſt, I ſhall not diſpute, but the way of Chriſt is ſometimes the ſame; His ſtays and reſerves ere he ſmiles upon a diſtreſſed ſoul, do make way for ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er endearing heart-breaking love to be let out upon it; And further indeed, As <hi>Joſephs</hi> Brethen were troubled at his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, between the two conſiderations
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119879:29"/>of the injuries they had done him, and the exceeding love he ſhewed them; As <hi>for Joſeph</hi> (ſay they) <hi>we ſold,</hi> &amp;c. ſo poor ſouls ſeeking Jeſus Chriſt, when he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears comfortably unto them, They are even troubled at Chriſts preſence, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the injuries they have done him, and the exceeding great love he hath ſhewed them, and this doth kindely melt the heart, when they wiſtly look him; Till Chriſt anſwer as <hi>Joſeph,</hi> ver. 5. of <hi>Gen.</hi> 45. <hi>Come hither,</hi> ſaith good <hi>Joſeph</hi> to his Brethren, <hi>for God did ſend me before to preſerve life;</hi> ſo ſaith the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, Ah poor ſoul, come hither, God did ſend me on purpoſe to preſerve thy ſoul, to bear thy ſins, to eſtabliſh a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of peace for thee; And how en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearing and melting is this to a ſoul that ſo enjoys him!</p>
               <p n="6">6. Chriſt thus withholding himſelf for a time, as it makes way for the greater joy and more abundant conſolation to a tempeſtuous ſoul, ſo it will make a ſoul more watchful and careful to keep Chriſt, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.4. I held him and would not let him go; If ſo tempeſtuous, periſhing, and ſuccourleſſe, when I enjoyed him not; Oh let them never take away my
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119879:29"/>Lord; Here, Here, (his Soul claſping him) let him lodge; One hour of his fellowſhip, is a heaven; Oh no, thou muſt not go, my deareſt Lord, 'till I go with thee and lie in thy boſome to all eternity; I will love thee and honour thee while I am here, and therefore do not, ah do not depart from me, I will not let thee go: But of this more in the cloſe.</p>
               <p>Is it ſo then, that Chriſt may for a time cloud himſelf from a poor ſoul at his feet, why then, Soul, let me return to the firſt poſture I ſtated thee in, in this Point; Art thou one that haſt ſaid ſeriouſly within thy ſelf from the ſight of thy helpleſſe condition, <hi>I will ariſe now and go about,</hi> Cant. 3.2. I have been ſitting all this while in the ſhadow of the vain world; But now, I will ariſe and ſeek him who hath life and peace in himſelf, though but now, yet I will enquire of the watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men after him, <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>I will wait at the poſts of his doors,</hi> his bleſſed and powerfull Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, till my ſoul findes him; Well, Take with thee this leſſon, If thou findeſt him not in joy and comfort, aſſoon as thou expecteſt; Here's encouragement for thee, not no give off thy purſuit, as
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119879:30"/>Satan and thy own unbeleeving heart will be ſtill prompting thee; To return to thy former eaſe and peace in ſinne and vanity, and the world again, or that thou hadſt a good intereſt enough in Chriſt before thou thus troubledſt thy ſelf, or it may be Satan will ſuggeſt, it is too late for thee, and thy day of grace is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, becauſe thou haſt ſleighted many; Well (I ſay) let none of theſe prevail with thee; Thou heareſt upon what weighty and endearing Reaſons Chriſt may for a time withhold comfort and peace; therefore let deniall encreaſe thy diligence, and not dead and flat it: Thou ſeeſt (Soul) that if thou wilt have Jeſus Chriſt, that he hath other work beſides filling thee with perfumes, and ſtaying thee with flaggons of love; And if thou beeſt truly convinced of ſin, and ſo of thy abſolute need of Chriſt, thou wilt be glad of him, and ſeek to him for thoſe works too; He hath ſtrong-holds of ſinne to break down; He hath Atheiſm Pride, Self-love, Obſtinacy, all manner of fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and earthy luſts to ſubdue within thee, that have by nature the poſſeſſion of thy heart, and theſe will grapple with him, and are unwilling to let thy heart go; all
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:119879:30"/>theſe unclean ſpirits muſt be caſt out, if thou wouldeſt have Chriſt dwell there; So that if thou wilt have him thou muſt have him on ſuch terms, thou muſt thus ſuffer him to prepare his way, to have a reſting-place within thee, And thoſe luſts muſt not domineer with him; If thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate within thy ſelf be rather to venture his loſſe then to part with the old gueſts of thy heart that he wold caſt out, then thou doſt not yet know what belongs to the guilt, and filth, and reign of ſinne, which thou wilt cry to be rid of, when thou truly ſeeſt what miſchief it hath done thee: If that be indeed the terms thou inſiſteſt on, 'tis but a little ſtirring of meer naturall conſcience, and not the convictions of the Spirit; Many ſouls, no doubt, from ſome ſuch temporary common enlightning of the natural con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, go and make an eſſay at Chriſt, liking well of peace and ſalvation, but finding that luſts muſt die for it, they give up the purſuit again, or elſe will have him (pretend to have ſo) and make him lodge with their unclean luſts, to protect and countenance them, and ſo make him a half-Chriſt, divide his work, make him indeed (like thoſe blaſphemers in the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:119879:31"/>Goſpel) to have an unclean Spirit, and ſin to be nothing; As many wretches in this age do aſſert, and indeed all carnall profeſſors of Chriſt do in their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations imply, when they ſerve their luſts, and cry Chriſt, Chriſt; No Soul, yeeld up a heart freely to him, and let him make one luſt after another bleed for it, Let him make good his way and poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Let him ſubdue all oppoſition in thy heart. and lay low all the crooked waies of it, and ſee what a Temple he will make for himſelf in the cloſe; In a word, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, and hold out in his ſtrength, and thou ſhalt have more then thy er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Learn well from hence to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Chriſts meaning in his invitations, not as if the thing promiſed were all to be enjoyed in a moment: Thou maieſt reſt confident in this, that the heart of Chriſt will be true to thee in them, though thou waiteſt for a time, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that one hour of his joy, is worth the waiting of an age, much more a heaven and eternity by it; And 'tis an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reſt thou ſeekeſt in him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. It chides the repinings of our hearts againſt this way of dealing by the Lord
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:119879:31"/>Chriſt, It rebukes all our hard thoughts of him, though he ſtay a little when we cry after him; Oh be contented for his wiſedom and love to order all things for his more ſweeter welcome, and more ſure and comfortable abode with thee; But yet to a ſoul under the impatiency of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of ſpirit,</p>
               <p n="1">Conſider 1. Doſt thou truly come to Chriſt, as before, doſt thou frequently ſpread thy caſe before him, and pleade his own bowells, free invitations, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, his intereſt with his Father, with him; ſome lie repining, but not earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly follow Chriſt for what they want, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Conſider duly, If there be no A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, luſt, that holds up its head, and would not yeeld, that is as a right hand, or right eye; go to God for a more narrow ſearch of thy heart; ſay, (as <hi>David</hi>) <hi>Search me, prove me,</hi> and <hi>try me;</hi> If there be any iniquity in my heart un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcovered, reveal and mortifie it at the very root.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider, that though thou haſt not ſenſible comfort, yet thou art ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the Lord in thy preſent condition, which thou maiſt indeed conſider with comfort, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 63.8, <hi>My ſoul followeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:119879:32"/>thee, and thy right hand upholdeth me;</hi> So continue to follow hard after God, and if thou findeſt his right hand, his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſuſtaining thee, thou maiſt conclude as <hi>David,</hi> v. <hi>laſt of that Pſalm, But I ſhall rejoyce in God,</hi> &amp;c. thou ſhalt be ſatisfied with his goodneſſe; yea, if thou finde ſuch promiſe breaking in upon thy ſpirit, and thou gathereſt ſupport from it, it may be an evidence, a love-token to thee, that God is in a way of love and comfort to thee.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Conſider, that faith and ſenſible en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of Gods love do not inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly go together, are not the ſame, as ſome poor creatures be apt to fancy; 'tis faith and not ſenſe, therefore learn to live by faith and not by ſenſe.</p>
               <p>But yet may ſome poor Soul ſay, This doth not come to the height of thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, the very ſtrength of this tempeſt in the conſcience being upon thee; Ah thou art a forlorn, tempeſtuous ſoul in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, thou ſaiſt: why now then, I will particularly deal with thee.</p>
               <p>Reade thy condition in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 54.8,9,10,11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'Tis ſpoken of the State of the Church, but as truly applicable to thy condition; <hi>v.</hi> 6. the Lord hath called
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:119879:32"/>thee as a woman forſaken and grieved in Spirit: yea, <hi>v.</hi> 11. <hi>Oh thou afflicted, toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with tempeſt, and not comforted;</hi> that fits thee; See <hi>v.</hi> 7, 8. <hi>For a ſmall moment have I forſaken thee, but with great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies will I gather thee: In a little wrath I hid my face from thee, but with everlaſting kindeneſſe will I have mercy on thee, ſaith the Lord thy Redeemer;</hi> A ſmall moment, and a little wrath, but great and everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting kindeneſſe; But may not the Lord, if he pleaſe, reſerve and withhold theſe from poor creatures that come thus af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and toſſed with tempeſt? I anſwer from <hi>ver.</hi> 9, 10. <hi>For this is as the waters of Noah unto me, for as I have ſworn that the waters of Noah ſhould no more go over the earth; ſo have I ſworn that I would not be wroth with thee nor rebuke thee; For the mountains ſhall depart, and the hills be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, but my kindeneſſe ſhall not depart from thee, neither ſhall the covenant of my peace be removed, ſaith the Lord that hath mercy on thee;</hi> Here's the Oath of God upon it, and ſooner ſhall the waters co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the earth again, and the mountains remove themſelves, then the Lord rebuke and utterly caſt off ſuch a ſoul; Neither ſhall <hi>the Covenant of his peace be removed,</hi>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:119879:33"/>that is, as God tenders a new agreement, and to be at peace with ſinners, conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted he is, yea, infinitely deſirous of it; Can he then caſt off a ſoul that comes tendring it ſelf for peace with him, that laies hold on his Covenant, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 59.6.</p>
               <p>But yet further will a weak miſ-giving heart be reaſoning againſt God and it ſelf; I fear, for all this, that 'tis in vain for me to ſeek, my heart ſinks within me; Now mark what the Lord ſaith to this, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.19. <hi>I have not ſpoken in ſecret, in a dark place of the earth; I ſaid not unto the Seed of Jacob, Seek me in vain; I the Lord ſpeak in righteouſneſſe, and declare things that are right:</hi> This the Lord doth not reſerve as a ſecret, but would have it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed on the houſe top; Let it be known to every poor weak ſoul that ſeeks me, It ſhall not be in vain; As if it were laid down on purpoſe (as indeed it is) to anſwer ſuch a fond reaſoning: And further (ſaith he) <hi>I the Lord ſpeak righteouſneſſe,</hi> I do not trifle with and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude ſouls, but ſpeak in good earneſt <hi>the things that are right,</hi> and <hi>v.</hi> 22. <hi>I am a juſt God,</hi> true to my word, and therefore not to be reaſoned againſt by men or devils;
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:119879:33"/>Away then with ſuch debates as thou doſt foſter in thy heart, yea, with ſuch vile diſputings againſt God, as to ſay within thy ſelf, 'Tis too late, 'Tis in vain, my caſe is deſperate, God will not hear, and therefore why ſhould I ſeek? To what purpoſe is it? Is not this to belye the wiſe and holy, and faithfull God, ſo to adde abundantly to thy former iniquity? In a word, If thou doſt ſeek and venture, and try what God will do, if thou art at laſt caſt off, thou canſt but be damned; And thy ſeeking, if thou couldſt fail, will rather be a mitigation of thy torment then an encreaſe.</p>
               <p>Well, but yet further may a Soul ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject (for the devil hath a world of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry this way) If I ſhould be ſtirred up to ſeek, upon theſe grounds, how ſhall I be aſcertain'd that theſe promiſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to me? Why, mark thou, doſt thou not ſay, I am an afflicted ſoul, diſquieted, toſſed with tempeſt, and in thy own thoughts forſaken? And ſaiſt, moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that thou art contented to ſeek and wait, ſeeing at worſt, thou canſt be no looſer by it; why then by what plea art thou excluded, what law, or what caveat is put in againſt thee? perhaps thou wilt ſay,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119879:34"/>thy ſinning with ſo high a hand againſt thy God, with many grievous aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting circumſtances; Why, finful worm, know 'tis written as clear as the Sun, if thou knowſt any thing of the Goſpel and minde of Chriſt, that no ſinner is exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from acceptance, from the greatneſſe of ſin, but for want of coming to Chriſt that he might have life, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5. as hath been ſhew'd; The truth is, thou art un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to be beholden to Chriſt, or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient to ſtay his leiſure, or elſe art re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to beleeve the lies of the devil a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, or elſe thou wouldſt not thus parley againſt him; Therefore bow thy ſelf at his feet, and pleade his own argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that he hath left for thee in his word, and do not ſtand asking whether theſe promiſes belong to thee, for they are as much thine, as any ſouls in the world, if thou wilt pleade them.</p>
               <p>But yet further may a poor ſoul com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain; Ah, I have a dull, dead, heavy, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed heart, heartleſſe am I to ſeek and cry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I have ſhewed before, that if thou wilt ask a heart, <hi>I will give it thee,</hi> ſaith the Lord, and ask his Spirit to raiſe up thy heart above that indiſpoſed di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper: Nay Soul, let me ask thee, Canſt
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:119879:34"/>thou truly complain of and feel ſuch a diſtemper, oh what a dull, heavy, dead, indiſpoſed heart have I? 'Tis of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of life within thee, or thou couldſt not ſo complain; And 'tis an earneſt of more of the ſpirit to be given unto thee, from what hath been now and before ſaid unto thee: Soul, maiſt thou be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to ſeek and wait privately, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, be diligent in all means, yea, with ſome meaſure of contentedneſſe, till the Lord ſhall ſpeak, and when thy ſpirit is ſo ſubdued, uſually comfort is not farre off; But as to thy further encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, I will leade thee on to the next Point.</p>
               <p>Thus having ſhew'd the condition of a humbled convinced ſinner, coming to Jeſus Chriſt in a periſhing condition, and waiting for the voice of comfort and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, I ſhall in the next endeavour to ſtate ſuch a faith which Chriſt in the Text cals a little faith; <hi>Why are ye fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="observation">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 4.</note>
                  <hi>True faith may be conſiſtent with many fears and weakneſſes, and yet may engage the heart of Chriſt to ſuccour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By what hath been opened, we may give forth this deſcription of faith; 'Tis
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119879:35"/>a coming to Chriſt in a periſhing condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ſalvation; which Divines uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtile faith of recumbency, relying and rowling upon Chriſt, which is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies accompanied with aſſurance, this being but the height and excellency of faith, not of the abſolute being of it, that is, that without which faith cannot be; So aſſurance is not of the nature of faith.</p>
               <p>That which I am to clear, is, <hi>That this Faith may be conſiſtent and mixt with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fears, and that yet it may engage the heart of Chriſt to ſuccour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. From example, <hi>Mar.</hi> 9.22,24. <hi>Lord, I beleeve, help thou my unbelief;</hi> Faith ſo weak, that he knew not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he might venture to call it faith or not; I beleeve, but ſtraight takes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf off, as if he were afraid to ſtile it faith, Lord, help mine unbeleef; or if I do not beleeve, Lord help me to beleeve, In ſuch a ſuſpenſe the words imply him to be, and yet 'twas a faith that ſped in its errand; So <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.2. In the caſe of the Leper, <hi>Lord, if thou wilt thou canſt make me clean;</hi> I beleeve thou haſt power e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, but whether thou wilt receive and help ſuch a miſerable creature, that's
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119879:35"/>a hard queſtion, He only viewed the power of Chriſt, but much doubted what his heart might be toward him; In the commended faith of the Centurion, <hi>v.</hi> 6. he only ſpreads the poor creature before him, comes to him, and 'twas enough, <hi>v.</hi> 13. <hi>As thou haſt beleeved, ſo be it unto thee, and he was healed the ſame hour;</hi> So <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.20, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the caſe of the diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed woman; firſt, ſhe came behinde him from her ſelf-unworthineſſe, and ſo doubting and fearing to come before his face, <hi>ſhe ſaid within her ſelf,</hi> ſhe had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parlies and reaſonings within her ſelf, whether ſhe ſhould go to him or not, but at laſt reſolved on it, and to do it by ſtealth; ſee the ſame laid down by <hi>Mark</hi> 5.33. 'tis there expreſſed, ſhe came fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and trembling, no queſtion, as doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of her acceptance, fell down before him in acknowledgement how unworthy a creature ſhe was for his notice, <hi>and told him all the truth,</hi> what a deſpicable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhe was, how <hi>ſhe had ſpent all ſhe had,</hi> and now muſt be helped by him, or pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and ſo miſery had made her bold, and ſhe ventured to come to him, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what a mercifull man he was; The very poſture of a poor humbled ſoul in
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119879:36"/>its need, a poor open-hearted ſinner coming to him; and then obſerve, how ready the Lords anſwer was, no accuſing her and reaſoning the matter with her, to tax her of her unworthineſſe, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeaks her kindely, <hi>Daughter, be of good comfort, thy faith hath made thee whole, go in peace, and be whole;</hi> The very errand a poor ſoul comes to Chriſt for: And 'tis very remarkable what Chriſt anſwered to the two blinde men coming to him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.28. <hi>Beleeve ye that I am able to do this?</hi> Only if he was able, not whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he was willing; If it be objected, all theſe were for temporall bleſſings, I anſwer, That under theſe, ſpiritual mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and ſalvation are couched, or if not there's the ſame reaſon of both; yea, further to clear this, if you will look into the hiſtories of thoſe eminent beleevers and Saints, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. do but mark what weakneſſes you may finde in their faith, <hi>Sarah</hi> her ſelf, if you look to <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. ſhe laughed within her ſelf, and ſaid, <hi>Shall it be ſo?</hi> a high queſtioning of the word of the Lord, and that upon which ſhe reſted, was the power of God only, which the Angels gave forth in that confirming word, <hi>Is there any thing too hard for the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119879:36"/>Lord?</hi> and ſo of <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf, that God was able to preſerve, Concerning his heart and willingneſſe, of that no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Reaſons.</hi>
                  </note>We ſhall enquire into the Reaſons of this, Why Faith is mixt with ſuch fears?</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe fleſh and bloud is againſt beleeving, the wiſedom of the fleſh is highly againſt it; for a ſoul to go out of it ſelf to another for righteouſneſſe; the wiſedom of fleſh and bloud is full of theſe <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5. imaginations, reaſonings, and diſputings againſt it; 'tis againſt the pride of fleſh and bloud to be beholden to another for righteouſneſs againſt all thoſe iſſues of pride, ſelf-love, ſelf-ſufficiency, and ſelf-confidence; Now fleſh and bloud being thus ſet againſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving in the Lord Jeſus, 'tis diſputing and reaſoning againſt it, as <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.12,13. <hi>which were born, not of bloud, nor of the fleſh, nor of the will of man, but of God;</hi> So when <hi>Peter</hi> Mat. 16. had confeſſed his faith, ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Fleſh and Bloud hath not revealed this unto thee, but my Father which is in heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Man is naturally under a power of unbelief, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.31. <hi>concluded under un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief;</hi>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:119879:37"/>not only a heart unapt to beleeve, but under a power of the contrary, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. ult. <hi>They could not enter in becauſe of their unbelief,</hi> a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, an impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity from unbelief, while remaining ſo; Now this power is not wholly vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſubdued, but will ſtill be mixing and riſing up, and oppoſing more or leſs in all beleevers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. A Soul findes nothing in himſelf to encourage him to beleeve, as in the caſe of <hi>Peter</hi> at his converſion, <hi>Luk.</hi> 5.8. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me Lord, for I am a ſinfull man;</hi> ſo when the voice of the Lord is heard in the ſoul, it fears before him, and begins to ſee to purpoſe, that he is a ſinfull crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, it is ready to depart from the Lord, and to bid the Lord depart from him; that which indeed ſhould have been <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> ground of going to Chriſt, or to have beſought him to come to him, his being a ſinfull man, he uſeth as a reaſon to bid the Lord depart from him; Lord canſt thou endure to look upon ſuch a ſinfull worm, ſuch a filthy wretch as my ſelf; Oh 'twill offend thy pure eyes but to glance upon me: So the Centurion, <hi>Maſter, I am not worthy thou ſhouldſt come under my roof;</hi> Senſe of unworthineſſe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119879:37"/>cauſeth a Soul to put up hard pleas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it ſelf, and ſo the heart being ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up and overwhelmed, and abaſed in the ſenſe of ſelf-vileneſſe and unworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, forgets and dares not ſo heartily pleade Chriſts free grace and tenderneſſe to receive it.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The accuſations of conſcience being awakened as before, muſtering up ſinne upon ſin, joyned with the aggravations of Satan, like a cunning diſputer, who muſters up all his forces, to make ſin as horrible as ever he argued it pleaſant and commodious, yea, his chief darts lie at the faith of a beleever, to be reaſoning againſt the grounds of beleeving, queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning their election, ſevering the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes out of their ſight, mudding and darkening their ſight of Chriſt, accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them for unſound and hypocrites, tempting them from means which make for ſtrengthening of faith; <hi>Peter</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>Satan hath deſired to winnow thee, but I have prayed that thy faith fail not,</hi> implying, Satans deſign lay moſt againſt his faith; through the malice and ſubtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Satan faith is put hard to it, till the Lord rebuke him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Faith is wrought forth gradually in
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119879:38"/>the ſoul by degrees, at firſt ſown as a grain of muſtard-ſeed, a ſmall ſeed; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions and reaſonings like overſpread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing tares ready to choak it, therefore being ſown, as I may ſo ſpeak, in weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, at firſt, 'tis thus put to it for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; therefore <hi>Paul</hi> tels the <hi>Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> 1 Theſ. 3.10,13. that there was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing lacking in their faith, and the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of their faith is much praied for by him.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Lord ſuffers it to be ſo, that his power in the ſupporting of a weak ſoul may the more appear: Faith is called the <hi>operation of the Son of God,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 2. and <hi>that your faith might ſtand in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God;</hi> when a ſoul is full of fears and miſ-givings, and ready to ſink under them, theu the hand of the Lord is more viſible in ſuſtaining, then we ſee by his power alone we ſtand; Had we a ſtrong ſetled faith preſently, we ſhould rather be lifted up in our ſelves, or reſt upon grace received, and ſo not glorifie the Lord Jeſus, and live upon him for ſtrength as he requires; Therefore the Lord ſuffers theſe fightings and reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings within, that we might have continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all recourſe to him for ſupport, and that
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119879:38"/>we might ſee that the beginnings, life, and growth of faith, it is all in and from Jeſus Chriſt as the Authour and Finiſher of it.</p>
               <p>For theſe Reaſons, <hi>viz.</hi> the wiſedom and pride of fleſh and bloud, the natural power of Unbelief not being wholly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, ſenſe of unworthineſſe, the depth of guilt, accuſations of conſcience, and the diſputings of Satan, faith ſown in weakneſſe at firſt, and all this ſuffered to ends of glory to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that his power and grace may be the more magnified, therefore true faith is mixt with many reaſonings, doubtings, miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings, diſputings, fears, which do an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy it.</p>
               <p>I will firſt endeavour to apply this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I prove further that ſuch a faith may engage Chriſt to ſuccour.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If true faith be thus mixt with fears and reaſonings; It meets firſt with the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie faith that the moſt of people pleaſe themſelves in, as I thank God I alwaies beleeved, God forbid but I ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in Jeſus Chriſt; 'Tis eaſie, very ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie indeed, to preſume away a precious ſoul, 'tis eaſie to flatter a mans ſelf with an opinion of beleeving, and indeed 'tis
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119879:39"/>nothing elſe but a cuſtomary opinion of Chriſt; But to beleeve in Chriſt Jeſus, and ſavingly and effectually to apply his bloud by his Spirit enabling, this is hard, ah hard indeed to a poor convinced ſoul, that hath deep thoughts of heart about the pardon of ſins; Lord, help my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, and Lord, if thou wilt, and the like; This eaſie beleeving is the dead ſleep of ſin upon the conſcience, and a generall opinion in the brain, that Chriſt died for ſinners, even for all ſinners to whom he is preached, heightned by the ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion of the devil, whoſe work it is to perſwade ſouls that have nothing but a dead, generall faith, that they beleeve well, and on the contrary to diſpute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the faith of true beleevers, that they do not truly believe. And this among others may be a diſcovery of true faith, unbelief is ſtill mixing, and Satan diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting againſt it, as in the reaſons ſhew'd. If ſo much faith againſt beleeving par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of ſinne in the Lord Jeſus, how can it chooſe but be ſo, but it muſt be a hard thing to a poor ſoul to faſten upon Chriſt in a promiſe for remiſſion of ſins, when ſo much oppoſition to it; Therefore this is an infallible note, true beleevers deeply
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:119879:39"/>feel and are humbled for unbelief; Oh 'tis the deep evil of their hearts, and that they moſt tremble at; but take a carnall, formall, dead-hearted Proteſtant, and no ſuch matter with him; He could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve a thouſand years together, and if he have any ſcruples, they be as nothing, a little praier or the like will quickly hekl it.</p>
               <p>And herein alſo is another great ſnare; Naturall conſcience, that is, a conſcience not ſavingly enlightned and ſanctified, may give ſome checks before, in, or after the commiſſion of a ſin, and then unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate perſons do moſt uſually gather, that they have truth of grace, becauſe they have ſome little conflicts within, which they faſten upon, from <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. <hi>the thing that I would not, that do I,</hi> but that former <hi>(I)</hi> is meant of the regenerate nature, diſtinct to, and warring againſt the fleſhly part, and not a little conflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the naturall conſcience from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon enlightenings of the word; So alſo as to doubting and ſome ſmall miſ-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings, theſe argue not a truth of ſaith, unleſſe theſe are only allayed by the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the ſoul to Jeſus Chriſt, and the evidence of the work of ſaith, with
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119879:40"/>power wrought forth in us; If thy doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings be ſuch, that do not ſettle again till thou haſt made a true entire cloſe with Jeſus Chriſt in ſelf-renouncing, then they are of the ſpirit, ſubduing ſin and unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in thee; Therefore look narrowly to unbelief, as true faith intereſts the ſoul in Chriſt, and all his grace and promiſes, ſo unbelief excludes while unſubdued, from all of Chriſt: It ſins againſt <hi>totum dei,</hi> every attribute of God; So then they could not enter in becauſe of unbelief; An utter impoſſibility upon it. And this may reign through deluded miſ-perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of true faith, though the converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the eye of men civil and regular. I deſire to acknowledge to the praiſe of the rich grace of God, that the opening of the power of unbelief by a holy Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of the Goſpel, was the firſt time of the Lords ſpeaking to me in powerfull convincement that I was in the ſtate of unbelief, though before full of confidence of the ſafety of my condition. Oh there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Soul, whoever thou art, be jealous of thy own heart in this particular, unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief is a cloſe, ſpirituall, undiſcerned evil, till the Lord come in and ſhew thee what the ſtrength of it is, by caſting in a grain
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119879:40"/>of faith to grapple with it, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the continuall ſupply of his Spirit, will be overwhelmed by it. Therefore let me preſſe thee with a ſerious triall of thy ſelf this way, that this is a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous ſnare, eaſineſſe to beleeve pardon of ſin and peace with God; So that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thou canſt make out a work of faith with power by the word and ſpirit; Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion all, and ſo in the ſight of thy meer naked condition, make out for Chriſt, as hath been before directed, as if thou wert before a ſtranger to him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If true Faith may conſiſt with ſo many fears and reaſonings; why then a word yet more to the convinced poor ſoul in its periſhing condition in it ſelf, that hath got a view of Chriſt, and is preſſing after him, but fears, ah ſad fears and miſ-givings ariſe. Why conſider this well, If it were not ſo thou mightſt juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly queſtion all indeed, whether any thing ſaving in thee; Tell me Soul, wouldeſt thou be again in the ſuppoſed ſafety thou waſt once in, when no ſuch conflicts in thee; No, thou wilt ſay, not fot a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand worlds, for then I was as a dead worm in ſin and unbelief; But thou wilt ſay yet I fear, Ah finde it hard to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:119879:41"/>and faſten upon and apply one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, ſo thou ſeeſt do all Gods children; Reade of and ask of any the holieſt and graciouſeſt, they will tell thee many a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious experience of this, what travels the poor ſoul hath had through doubtings, fears, ſinkings, cloudings, and yet all cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, ſweetly calmed again, as hath been ſhewed, and am yet further to declare, the ſtaies and the props of a poor ſoul in this caſe have been opened. But a word more, Is it no further with thee then this, then queſtioning of faith, with the <hi>Lord, help my unbelief;</hi> know, 'tis impoſſile to cry after Chriſt with complaints of Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, without ſome truth of faith; Canſt thou reach but unto the power of Chriſt, to give him the glory of being able to ſuccour thee, but doubteſt of his willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe what his heart may be unto thee; Ah, thou ſadly doubteſt; Is it with thee, Lord, if thou wilt? ſtill an If, know Faith on the power of Chriſt, as in the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſhewed, may be ſaving; Remember alſo Chriſts melting anſwers, <hi>I will, be thou clean; Be it unto thee as thou wilt, Go in peace;</hi> And this to ſuch ſouls who came beleeving in his power to ſave, though trembling what his heart might
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:119879:41"/>be towards them; I am now further to ſhew, that ſuch a weak purſuing Faith may engage Jeſus Chriſt to ſuccour, which hath received ſome demonſtration already; but 'tis further clear'd from theſe reaſons.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Faith though never ſo weak, be it faith (that is, ſuch that reſolves the ſoul to venture all with Chriſt, and purſue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him) is a beam from Chriſt himſelf, ſhed by his own ſpirit; 'Tis the ſpirit ſo enabling the ſoul to chooſe and follow Chriſt, therefore Chriſt will own ſuch a faith, and 'twill engage his whole heart to more.</p>
               <p n="2">2. 'Tis that grace by divine appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which engageth all the priviledges and bleſſings of Chriſt to a ſoul; Not from any worthineſſe in it, but by Gods own Ordination; So that a Soul is not ſo much to reaſon thus, Can ſuch a poor, weak faith engage Chriſt? but he is to look to Gods Ordination and promiſe that it ſhall. In a word, Not to be poring upon the weakneſſe of faith, but to be eying and conſidering the free promiſe, and ſo not to make an eſtimate of thy faith by preſent ſenſible enjoyment and feelings of comfort, but by thy going out
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:119879:42"/>to Chriſt in the indefinite free invitement and promiſe to all humble comers for life and ſalvation; and then ſay and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon within thy ſelf; The Soul that accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Chriſts own invitement, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and promiſe, renounceth all other, and comes and follows him for life, ſhall have and finde life in him; But ſo doth this poor trembling ſoul of mine (if I know any thing of my own heart) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all other, and flies to a power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, free-hearted Jeſus, mighty to ſave; Therefore I ſhall finde him, yea, I have him; And this a true Scripturall ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al reaſoning, grounded upon Chriſts own words, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.40. <hi>Joh.</hi> 6.37. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.17. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.15.</p>
               <p>But now, if thou yet feareſt and art jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous whether thy ſelf-renouncing and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to and cloſing with Chtiſt be full and entire; The next and every time thou goeſt to him and pleadeſt with him (and do it often) proteſt againſt all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther helps, and now there is no witneſſe but God and thy own conſcience, that thou doſt periſh in all opinion of thy ſelf or any other, all the ſtrength and righteouſneſſe that thy ſelf and all the world to help thee hath, being but as dead
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:119879:42"/>water to thee, and that thou doſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt againſt them, and ſo make an entire cloſe with the Lord Jeſus alone, that he may be thine and thou maiſt be his, in Goſpel terms, and that thou art willing to take up his yoke and follow him; Know alſo that ſuch jealouſies of thy ſelf are a good argument of ſomething ſound within thee.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Further, If through thine unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with the Scriptures thou runſt upon a miſtake, and conceiveſt that true faith conſiſts in a full perſwaſion and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of ſalvation; Thou muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that it is not ſo; for aſſurance is the height and excellency of faith, ſuch a degree that many gracious ſouls are long ere they attain to it, yea, have only ſome ſhort glimpſes of in this life; And though ſome arrive to a greater meaſure of joy and aſſurance in the holy Ghoſt, yet not enjoy'd by any in a conſtant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, while a bitter root of unbelief re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in us.</p>
               <p>I do not here intend to give forth the conſequent evidences and fruits of faith, only a word or two, as to the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a weak faith, while thou art thus in thy doubtings, or if faith lie as it
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119879:43"/>were dead, and doth not act lively upon Chriſt; Though in ſuch a caſe thou art to be ſtirring up every grace, yet do not ſtand poring upon ſuch a heavy frame of heart, nor do thou think to lift up the hand of faith by thy own power, but go and lie before Chriſt, go forth from thy own heart to him, to requicken the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of faith, that thou maiſt draw new life from him, and this follow him for: And then though faith be even as a wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered hand (as ſometimes it is) Chriſt will ſpeak to thy ſoul, as to the man with a withered hand in the Goſpel, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Stretch forth thy hand,</hi> and thou ſhalt do ſo, and embrace Chriſt in thy arms, and thine affections run forth lively upon him. It may be objected, Is it ſafe then to let doubtings and fears lie and be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of them, ſeeing thus mixing they do evidence truth of faith; No, but la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to get them ſuppreſt and ſubdued by the power and ſpirit of Chriſt; Though it be not abſolutely thy duty to have aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, yet 'tis thy duty to labour and give all diligence to gain it, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. But eſpecially beware of ſuch things which do deaden and ſtagger faith, and ſome of thoſe I will point out to thee,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:119879:43"/>as to the caſe of a young convert.</p>
               <p n="1">1. After conviction, enlightening, and in ſome meaſure a ſelf-emptying and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing, as hath been ſhewed, and ſo a ſight of free-grace and Chriſt to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie from ſin, and a rowling the ſoul upon it, and alſo ſome delightfull ſavour of it; Then the main temptation is to become negligent in duty: As to neglect humble, awfull, diligent, waiting upon God in prayer, and other Ordinances: This rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning being upon a young convert, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our duty and obedience doth not juſtifie us before God, therefore for no other purpoſe; But this is a dangerons ſnare, and too many poor ſouls endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered with it; Neglect of duty begets a vain and a wanton ſpirit, and cauſeth the Lord to withdraw from us, and will ſtagger faith, and cauſe thee to queſtion any work upon thy ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Sleightneſſe of Humiliation for for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſins in our unregenerate ſtate begets a dead and ſlight ſpirit; Though they are not to be remembred after effectuall calling, as now able to condemn us, and God declares in his Covenant of grace to forget them alſo, to remember them no more againſt us, yet they are not to
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:119879:44"/>be forgotten to other conſiderations, <hi>viz.</hi> that we may be the more humbled and abaſed before the Lord, that we may loathe our ſelves in our former deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble waies, and the ſenſe of the pardon of them may the more melt our hearts; <hi>Eze.</hi> 36.31. <hi>Zech.</hi> 12.10. Therefore after grace received 'tis good to be frequent in the renewing of ſerious and through, and as particular as may be, humiliation for ſins of unregeneracy though pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to us and changed from them.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Too familiar converſe with carnall company, haply ſuch which before our calling we did moſt frequently converſe with, this will deaden our ſpirits, and beget diſcomfort, when a convert will not own and acknowledge to the praiſe of the rich and free grace of God, the change and work the Lord hath wrought upon him; And ſo the want of that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, compoſed, reſerved, wary carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age and demeanour anſwerable to a change upon the inward man, which will alſo quickly beget deadneſſe, ſtaggering, diſcomfort.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Either a neglectfull, or a curious, criticall hearing the Goſpel preached, as to judge of the gifts and parts of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:119879:44"/>which will at laſt grow to a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of fancy, rather then to a trembling at the word, that it may puriſie and aſſure the heart; This joyned with a negiect of reading the Scriptures, or reading them out of a curious enquiry to be able to ſpeak diſcerningly before others, to have praiſe of men; This will alſo quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſe a ſtaggering.</p>
               <p n="5">5. As conſequentiall of this latter, a ſelf-conceit of knowledge and parts, growing to an over-weaned conceit of our ſelves; This ſelf-conceit is the main bait of Satan in young converts, and the cauſe of many after-trials, till a through diſcovery of it, and ſo a mortifying of it, uſually by afflictions, temptations, or deſertions, or all; No evil more natural then to be lifted up in our ſelves, to have an itch to appear to be ſome body, and to excell others, and to ſeek for gifts and graces, not ſo much to honour God with, as to pleaſe others, and to gain a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute with men; This to be lookt to with a godly jealouſie, as that which will cauſe a ſtaggering upon thy ſpirit at laſt.</p>
               <p n="6">9. The want of diligent ſearching our own hearts, from whence the former and other evils get ſtrength, and lie cloſe, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:119879:45"/>as to pride and hypocriſie, and ſo not attending to that main grace, which is the ſoul of all, ſincerity and ſimpliciy of heart, to aim at God and not at our ſelves; A ſlight practiſe of ſearching the more cloſe and ſpiritual corruptions begets an unſafe temper, and when they appear and the Lord gives a deeper diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of them, will ſtagger thy faith, and bring all afreſh into queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any ſoundneſſe at all in thee.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Not attending to growth in morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, ſincerity, zeal, and holineſſe, but to content our ſelves we are (we truſt) converted, therefore ſafe enough, much carnall joy mixing with that of the ſpirit; This growth upon a young con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert is apt for a time to be neglected, whereby faith is overgrown ere they are aware, and begin to be at a loſſe, till the Lord have a way to awaken them to it.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Inordinate enjoyment of any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-mercy, be it what it will, either by too affectionate purſuit, or delight in it, ſtaying upon and feeding upon the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and not carried up to Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe by it, and ſo not uſing it with a looſe heart; This is apt to bring many
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:119879:45"/>ſnares upon our ſpirits and waies, and at laſt to cauſe us to looſe the favour of God.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Want of a holy fellowſhip with ſuch who are godly, either by frequent conference, and communicating their experiences of God, ſpecially in a more holy Church-fellowſhip then the mixt Congregations are yet reduced into, which will abundantly quicken and ſtrengthen faith, and every gift and grace of beleevers, and maketh much for the retaining and encreaſe of comfort.</p>
               <p n="10">10. In a word, a ſlight frame of ſpirit, the heart not being daily awed with a holy fear of God, whereby light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and vanity, and diſcompoſure ariſeth; As alſo negligence in a mans calling, or in ſome duty to ſome relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>Theſe are the ſpeciall things which are apt to ſtagger and deaden Faith, to cauſe the Lord to withhold or withdraw com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, that we are brought to queſtion all again, whether any true ſaving work up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, to cauſe the Lord to let out ſore temptations upon us; or to lay his hand upon us, very uſually ſickneſſe, or croſſes in our eſtates or friends; And indeed,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119879:46"/>by theſe, a ſounder and deeper humilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is wrought forth, even a ſecond con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, when a narrower ſearch is ſet up in our hearts, and ſincerity, watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and other graces come more in view.</p>
               <p>Now as all thoſe evils, negligences, and defects do thus ſtartle, weaken faith, and hinder comfort, ſo a diligent care, oppoſite to all thoſe, as thou maiſt parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly review them, or means bleſſed of God to ſtrengthen faith and comfort, which I ſhall only mention, <hi>viz.</hi> Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in praier and every other duty, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing of humiliation, avoiding much converſe with carnall men, carefull at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending upon the Word preached, not with curioſity but humility; Not to be pufft up with ſelf-conceit of parts, ſearch for hypocriſie, attending to growth, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying the creatures with a looſe and mortified heart, the fellowſhip of the Saints, a ſerious frame of ſpirit, joyned with wiſedome and care as to all relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons towards God or man, theſe are the waies wherin God uſually ſheddeth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort upon his people.</p>
               <p>It may further be enquired, Whether faith will ever caſt out all fear? I anſwer.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:119879:46"/>It may in good meaſure keep under ſervile, baſe, disheartening fear; But there is a fear which is <hi>vigil animae,</hi> the watchman of the ſoul, a Servant to faith, which makes the heart not over-deſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and bears off ſecurity, and keeps all awake as the Centinell of the heart, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Let us therefore fear,</hi> &amp;c. And when the bleſſed intervals of joy and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance come, then let this fear be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and 'twill preſerve thee from wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toning with thy joy, that it mix not nor break out into carnall joy; And indeed, when ſuch a holy fear doth ariſe and min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle it ſelf with our joy, then it is moſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and doth beſt diſtinguiſh a fleſhly joy from a ſpirituall.</p>
               <p>And now having thus farre ſtated the caſe of a poor, willing, hardly-beleeving ſoul, as coming in a periſhing condition to Chriſt, with ſuch conſiderations, which may be for a ſtay unto it, till Chriſt ſpeak as in the Text, <hi>Why art thou fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full?</hi> We will now ſet the tempeſtuous Soul in this periſhing condition, in weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of faith before Jeſus Chriſt, and ſo briefly conſider what this rebuking voice of Chriſt is able to do; Only I will firſt queſtion with this fearfull ſoul, in Chriſts
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119879:47"/>words, <hi>Soul, why art thou fearfull?</hi> thou wilt anſwer readily, <hi>From thy ſins and unbelief.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Hath Jeſus Chriſt power enough to ſubdue them? Sure he hath, <hi>I will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due them,</hi> and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.13. <hi>I will work, and who ſhall let it, or turn it back?</hi> When he will work in any buſineſſe his Father hath committed to him, whereof this is one of the chief, even to receive and comſort weak ſouls that come unto him, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.10,11. <hi>Behold, the Lord God will come with ſtrong hand, and his arm ſhall rule for him, behold his reward is with him, and his work before him;</hi> What work is this he owns with ſo much power, and puts ſuch a <hi>Behold</hi> upon? See in the next verſe, <hi>He ſhall feed his Flock like a Shepherd, He ſhall gather the Lambs with his arm, and carry them with his boſome, and ſhall gently leade them that are with young:</hi> Now, mark Soul, Here's his power to work, and none, none ſhall turn it back, and the work thou haſt for him to do is his own work and buſineſſe, therefore with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement ſpread it before him, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to him, and neither ſins nor unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief ſhall ſtand before him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Is't his will and purpoſe to receive
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119879:47"/>ſuch a weakling? This hath been opened in part before; But conſider, Soul, 'twas his very purpoſe in coming down from heaven, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.8. and having wrought forth his purpoſe in order to it here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, Now he is paſſed into the Heavens to make it good to poor ſouls; to whom? to ſuch who come on ſet purpoſe for it; Therefore when 'tis Chriſts great pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that which his heart is full on, and alſo thou goeſt and ſeekeſt to him on purpoſe for it, what needſt thou ſtagger and be fearfull?</p>
               <p>Now that this is the work that is ſtill before Chriſt to do, and his purpoſe not changed, is left upon record in his laſt words to <hi>John,</hi> Rev. 22.17. <hi>Let him which is athirſt Come,</hi> which was ſpoken after his aſcenſion into glory.</p>
               <p>But ſtill it may be thy minde runs upon this, This power and purpoſe of Chriſt towards my ſelf, I beleeve in the general to be true of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but whether I am one of thoſe to whom it is meant. Mark, <hi>whoſoever will,</hi> anſwers that, as I have reaſoned before; Shew me how thou canſt exclude thy ſelf from that ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall invitement, or thou muſt grant it takes in thee alſo, that deſireſt to come
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:119879:48"/>to him; And if thou ſtill reaſoneſt, as to thy particular caſe, as receiving ſuch ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations which every ordinary ſinner doth not; I anſwer, There is no ſtating of caſes, but <hi>Whoſoever will,</hi> and <hi>whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is athirſt,</hi> know in a word, That 'tis written as with a beam of the Sun for clearneſſe, that the Goſpel excludes no ſoul from ſalvation, becauſe he is ſuch or ſuch a ſinner, but for not coming, in the ſenſe of it, to Chriſt, that he might have life in him; If thou ſhouldeſt catch at that, and ſay, Thou feareſt thou art not ſenſible enough; know that is a meaſure of ſenſibility of ſin, and ſuch as may up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a true account ſend to Chriſt; And therefore Soul, ſay what thou wilt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thy ſelf, and reaſon from thy ſelf, and ſo maiſt put in theſe demurres, do but eye Jeſus Chriſt in his power, purpoſe, free and generall invitement, and thou haſt no ground to be fearful: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore why art thou fearfull? Thou haſt no reaſon, if thou eyeſt Chriſt, to be ſo; ſpecially if thou conſider what is next to be opened.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="observation">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> 5.</note>
                  <hi>That Jeſus Chriſt can with a word re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke all the tempeſts and fears upon a poor ſoul coming and ſeeking to him;</hi> In the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119879:48"/>handling of which I ſhall be very brief.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He maketh the ſtorm a calm, ſo that the waves thereof are still,</hi> Pſa. 107.27. True in this caſe alſo; In <hi>Mar.</hi> 4, the parallel place to the Text, He ſaid unto the Sea, <hi>Peace, and be ſtill,</hi> and 'twas enough; He that could command the windes and Seas by his word, can much more ſtill the troubles and fears of a poor ſoul co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to him: This hath alſo in part been confirmed by obſerving the anſwers that Chriſt gave to thoſe who in ſuch diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult caſes came to him: <hi>Be thou clean, Go in peace;</hi> and theſe were preſently effect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the word of his mouth: As in the Creation of the word, God ſaid, <hi>Let there be,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and it was ſo;</hi> Now as to this work upon a poor ſoul, there's the ſame mighty power promiſed, and goes along with his word, which he ſpeaks in and by, in the Goſpel; <hi>Thou haſt the words,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter, of eternall liſe;</hi> 'Tis often cal'd, <hi>The Word of Life, The power of God, The arm of the Lord, The red of his Strength,</hi> even ſuch a power as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed <hi>Pſa.</hi> 29. The voice of the Lord upon the waters, The voice of the Lord is powerfull and full of Majeſty, it breaks
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:119879:49"/>the Cedars of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> and ſhakes the wilderneſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So is it able to ſubdue all the high things, all the reaſonings, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ſtrong holds and heights of our Spirits, It can make the wilderneſſe and the ſolitary place, the place of ſinging and of joy; even what the Pſalmiſt concludes in that Pſalm men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, at <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>The Lord will give ſtrength unto his people, The Lord will bleſs his prople with peace;</hi> And this is ſpoken as a concluſion to all thoſe mighty things that are ſpoken of the voice of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Much might be ſaid for the further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of this; but being a truth ſo clear and granted, I ſhall only briefly apply it.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi>
                  </note>I might return here to the dead-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed profeſſour, and inform him of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery by this Truth; That ſo much vertue and might in the holy Word of God, and he never felt this ſhaking or quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him: And thence that he might come under this, that no work of God with power upon his heart to this day, and ſo to counſell and encourage the poor, dead, blinde, deaf ſinners with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to attend upon Chriſts voice,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:119879:49"/>ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 43.8. <hi>Bring them to me;</hi> Haſt thou a heart like a wilderneſſe? come to him, and it ſhall bloſſome as the roſe; Haſt thou a heart of earth? I will ſmite it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 11. Nor ſins, nor luſts, nor bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſſe, nor earthlineſſe, nor deafneſſe, nor blindeneſſe, ſhall ſtand before him; Come then, oh come with ſuch and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation, and thou ſhalt know the mighty power of his word.</p>
               <p>But to the fearing Soul; I need not I hope further encourage thee to come to Chriſts Ordinances; Only a word, Haſt thou waited on them, but not a comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able anſwer yet? Conſider well, Haſt thou come to hear Chriſt ſpeak: <hi>I will hear what God the Lord will ſpeak,</hi> Haſt thou not too much hang'd on the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, upon his lips? This may be a ſnare: Eye the promiſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.19. <hi>I create the fruit of the lips, Peace, Peace, ſaith the Lord, and I will heal them,</hi> So <hi>Iſ.</hi> 55.10,11. ſpeaking of the word, <hi>It ſhall accompliſh that which I pleaſe;</hi> know: If all the hoſt of glorified Saints and Angels ſhould joyn with all the holy Preachers of the Earth, and ſhould encompaſſe thy ſoul, to ſpeak life or peace unto it, and beſeech thee to be comforted, unleſſe Chriſt ſpeak by
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:119879:50"/>them, 'twould be all fruitleſſe; Therefore get thy heart into a clear expectation for Chriſt to ſpeak to thy heart by the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, that is, to diſtill the dews and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations of his ſpirit by it, or all to no purpoſe. So the Spouſe <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.8. <hi>The voice of my Beloved.</hi> v. 10. <hi>My Beloved ſpake and ſaid unto me, Riſe up my Love, and fair One, and come away:</hi> So <hi>Gant.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Awake O North-winde, and come thou South, and blow upon my Garden, that the Spices thereof may flow out;</hi> which is the Spirit of Chriſt blowing upon the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, cauſing the vertues thereof to flow out; Therefore if thou ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueſt a diſquieted, fearing, periſhing ſoul, and pants after comfort and aſſurance; Pray thy heart may be raiſed up to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract from any power as the voice of man, but wait that the Spirit of Chriſt may breathe in the voice, and then thou art in a readier poſture for the Lord to rebuke the Tempeſt of fears upon thee. A poor Soul may take further encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement beſide the promiſes, from the bleſſed experiences of many and many a comfortleſſe creature, who after many tempeſts, periſhings, fears, ſinkings of ſpirit, have at laſt by waiting publikely
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:119879:50"/>and privately for Chriſts voice, found the rebuking power of it, and their diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers ſweetly allayed; And even a ſudden heavenly calm upon them, <hi>There was a great calm,</hi> ſaith the Text, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to ſmile; ſuch a calmneſſe, ſtillneſſe, ſuch a wonderful ſerenity that is after a ſtorm, when the heavens and the earth ſeem, as it were to ſmile; So Chriſt ſmiles upon a ſoul, having withheld his face and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and cauſeth a bleſſed ſerenity, clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, quietneſſe, to be upon it, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by a ſudden breaking in, ſometime by a ſecret graduall illapſing into a ſoul, that it becomes comforted it knows not how, ere it was aware: Oh bleſſed, for ever bleſſed the ſouls that wait and finde this, And finde it Soul thou ſhalt if thou art in this poſture deſcribed; Let the Storm be what it will, the clouds never ſo dark, one ray and beam from Chriſt ſhall raiſe even a heaven in thy Spirit, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus far have I brought a Soul botto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med upon free and faithfull promiſes, to the immediate expectation of Chriſt to rebuke the tempeſt and fears upon it, to ſuccour its periſhing condition; The Lord grant it may ſettle thee upon the power, promiſe, purpoſe, delight of the Lord
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119879:51"/>Jeſus to do it; I will a little ſpeak of the wonders thou maiſt expect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="observation">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Obſ.</hi> 6.</note>
                  <hi>The calmed Soul is filled with the wonders of Chriſts power and love;</hi> They marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, ſaying, What manner of man is this, that the Windes and the Sea obey him?</p>
               <p>His Name <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. is called <hi>Wonderfull,</hi> deſcribed to be <hi>Wonderfull in Counſell, Excellent in Working,</hi> Iſa. 28. <hi>laſt.</hi> We may view thoſe Meditations of the Saints, when thus in the admiration of his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull goodneſſe and ſweetneſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.5. <hi>Many O Lord my God are thy won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull works which thou haſt done, and thy thoughts which are to usward, they cannot be reckoned up in order unto thee, If I would declare and ſpeak of them, they are more then can be numbred;</hi> So <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34.2. &amp;c. <hi>My Soul ſhall make her boaſt in the Lord,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Oh magnifie the Lord with me, and let us exalt his Name together; I ſought the Lord and he heard me and delivered me out of all my ſears; This poor man cried unto him, and he ſaved him out of all his troubles: Oh taſte and ſee that the Lord is good, Bleſſed is the man that truſteth in him:</hi> Pſa. 36.7. <hi>How excellent is thy loving kindeneſſe, O God?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pſa.</hi> 116.7. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:119879:51"/>unto thy Reſt O my Soul,</hi> &amp;c. And what ſhall I render unto thee? So <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.18,19. The Church is brought in ſo admiring Chriſt, <hi>Who is a God like unto thee</hi> (why?) <hi>that pardoneſt iniquity, and paſſeſt by tranſgreſſions?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>He will turn again</hi> (though he hide his face) <hi>he will have compaſſion upon us;</hi> yea, it will break forth, Come, and hear all ye that fear God, and I will declare what he hath done for my Soul; yea, then Soul, thou ſhalt know, what is the <hi>exceeding great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his power towards them that beleeve, according to the working of his mighty pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> Eph. 1.19. Theſe wonders of Chriſts power and love will be thus enlarged in thy ſoul: Oh the wonders of his power! Who is like unto thee Indeed, Lord, who waſt able at firſt to lay hold of me, and take me as a brand out of the fire? Oh, Am I not ſaved as a brand out of the fire? <hi>Zech.</hi> 3.2. Thou who waſt able to ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, Live, when I was in my bloud; dead as a ſtone in my ſins: Thou who waſt able to ſubdue all the ſtrong rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion and obſtinacy of my heart; to turn the violent ſtream of it from earth to heaven; yea, thou waſt able to deal with all mine iniquities and corruptions, the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:119879:52"/>leaſt of which had been too ſtrong for me: yea, thou waſt able to rebuke all the tempeſtuous aſſaults of Satan, ſuch tempeſts, ſuch a periſhing condition, ſuch fears upon a poor ſoul, to command the waves to be ſtill, and they were ſo; Oh who is like unto thee my Almighty glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Lord? Joyn this to the greater wonders of thy free-love, who hadſt love and bowels enough to regard ſuch a rebellious wretch, when thus in his bloud, ſerving his luſts, and loving plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures more then God; When I was da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly and delightfully ſinning againſt thee; Oh infinite Love! to pity and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and ſuccour ſuch a poor, tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous wretch as I was after thou hadſt awakened me, when fitter, my ſelf being Judge, to have been a caſt-away from thy preſence for ever; Oh the Ocean of grace! Oh the wonders of thy love! Oh the unfadomed heights and depths of it! Eternity will but ſerve to admire and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore thee in it: So ſings the Spouſe in the Song, <hi>c.</hi> 3.6. filled with the loves of Chriſt, <hi>Who is this that cometh out of the Wilderneſſe like pillars of ſmoak, perfumed with Myrrhe and Frankincenſe, with all Powders of the Merchant,</hi> &amp;c. A little to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:119879:52"/>enlarge this, I will ſhew what conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions they are that make any work ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear wonderfull, and they will be found in this of the Lord Chriſts to his People.</p>
               <p n="1">1. A repugnancy in nature to the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect wrought forth, this cauſeth wonder; So is it in the whole work of Chriſt for us and in us; That which was for us, being but as one continued, rich, glorious my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.26. All of nature againſt it; As to his work in his people; what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctancy, obſtinacy, ſtrivings with the holy Spirit, before a proud, hard, rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious, ſelf-exalting heart will yeeld to bow before the Lord Jeſus? Not only liſtneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, heartleſneſſe, impotency, but a ſtrong enmity and reſolute oppoſition againſt the work of grace; yea, as to our caſe in hand, the quieting of the tempeſt upon a ſoul, what reſiſtency to comfort by the carnall part? what putting up of freſh reaſonings and doubtings, and will not beleeve Jeſus Chriſt upon his word, till the ſpirit of power perſwade, command, enables to do ſo?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Such things do beget wonder, which are unexpected or unhoped for; ſo is the firſt appearing and work of Chriſt to and in us; When a Soul ſecurely ſits with
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119879:53"/>folded arms in the ſhadow of death, in the groſſe darkneſſe that is naturally up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, the ſtrength of the heart after va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, when little expectation of ſuch a voice of Chriſt, as hath been ſhewed in the firſt, <hi>Ariſe, Awake, Come away,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Matthew</hi> ſitting at the Receipt of Cuſtom little expected that the Lord Chriſt (whom he never lookt after) ſhould come and ſpeak to him in ſuch a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding voice, and he ſhould preſently leave all, ſo wealthy an income, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a perſecuted Chriſt; He would have been like enough to have ſpit in the face of him who ſhould have propheſied ſuch a thing to him, as every ſinfull wretch is, till the Lords voice be heard within him; And ſo in the matter of comfort, when poor, and languiſhing, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining a tempeſt is up, then even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are aware, above what we durſt to expect, comes a Chriſt and ſpeaks and calms all.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Things formerly unknown to us, when they appear, beget wonder; ſo are the things that Chriſt works and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals to us; we are utterly ignorant, and know not what preciouſneſſe in Chriſt, rill he open his heart to us; What re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhings,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:119879:53"/>what treaſures of all goodneſs and ſweetneſſe are in him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Things that are ſeldome done beget wonder, ſo comparatively with the world of ſouls that are paſſed by, 'tis but ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and rare work for Jeſus Chriſt to lay hold upon ſouls, here and there a ſoul he chaſeth forth; And ſaith a poor delivered ſoul, What was I more then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, that the Lord ſhould paſſe by abundance of poor creatures, who haply never diſhonoured God ſo much as I have done? Oh this conſideration makes grace appear abundant and admirable, this is a heightning, enlarging Meditation upon a poor calmed ſoul indeed; In a word, the Lord Jeſus ſo convays himſelf to his own, that it ſhall be marvellous in their eyes; That they may attribute the firſt motion of light and life in the ſoul from him, the perfecting and continuing of it; That his children may be kept humble and lowly before him, and aſcribe all to him, and depend upon him, that they may have nothing to rejoyce in, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the name of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi>
                  </note>If a calmed ſoul be thus full of the wonders of Chriſts power and love; firſt By this any ſoul may know whether the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119879:54"/>calm that is upon his ſpirit be from Chriſt or not; If ſo, then his hand, his power, and love, is admired and extolled in it: Conſider therefore, any ſoul, by the way, What are the wondrous things upon thy Spirit? what are the things thou haſt deep thoughts of heart about? Canſt thou fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſay, Oh how wonderfull have been the thoughts of Chriſt towards me? what wonders hath he wrought for me and in me? Who is a God pardoning iniquity like unto thee? <hi>Mic.</hi> 7.18. That's the temper and voice of a pardoned ſoul; So he breaks out into the admiration of him: A pardoned Soul cannot have ſuch ſleight thoughts about it, as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to a dead hope of it have; If it be not ſo with thee, let me once more counſell thee to go to Chriſt and tell him what wonders thou heareſt he can doe; And pleade with him, that there's an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject before him to manifeſt one upon, even by raiſing up ſuch a worm, dead in ſin, as thou art, unto life; Tell him, he ſhall have the glory of the Miracle; Oh let him ſay unto thee, Live, and thou ſhalt live in his ſight.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If Jeſus Chriſt be able to work forth ſuch wonders upon and for poor
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119879:54"/>ſouls, <hi>Videant quam tutò ſe committunt Sancti,</hi> &amp;c. ſaith <hi>Bucer;</hi> See then how ſafely we commit our ſelves to ſuch a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot who can guide and anchor us through all ſtorms and difficulties, can ceaſe our tempeſts within or without, to make way for ſweeter Sun-ſhines and calms; And therefore ſhould not the Saints pierce through the thickeſt, darkeſt tempeſts, and hang upon him when all appears but in a periſhing way; yea, will not the Lord Jeſus pierce through them all to us, and make our hears melt with chiding us for our little faith? Say not, Fainting Soul, within thy ſelf, that becauſe 'twill be a wonderfull thing for thee to be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up, comforted, (whatever thy condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be) and therefore it will not be; No, No, Say, thou hangeſt upon a Chriſt whoſe works are all wonders, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſhall be ſo.</p>
               <p>And now what will this poor Soul do that is thus through the abundant grace of Chriſt ſilled in ſome meaſure with ſuch precious wonders of Chriſt, when it is bleſſedly calmed by Chriſts refreſhing voice, (For ſo I will now ſuppoſe that ſoul either already, or ſhall be ſo, who hath been or is in this tempeſtuous pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:119879:55"/>condition at Chriſts feet) and is or ſhall be thus calmed, Will it not to this purpoſe break forth, O welcome ten thouſand times ſweeteſt Chriſt, Come, Lodge for ever in my ſoul (though a mean habitation) for I cannot let thee go; Ah, will not that ſoul ſtudy returns of love and honour to Jeſus Chriſt? Will it not love him and love him more abundantly? Will it not lay it ſelf at his feet to be diſpoſed by him? Will it not ſmile upon and embrace reproaches for him? Shall any thing be too dear and precious to part with for Chriſt? No, It ſhall not: Shall the purſuit of empty creatures come in competition with him? Let me ask thee Soul in earneſt, Wilt thou? canſt thou ſeek great things for thy ſelf, and let Chriſts honour be ſlighted? Go then and daily treat with Chriſt to this purpoſe, Say unto him, Maſter, Maſter, what ſhall I do for thee? For whom ſhall I live and die but for thee? Dear Lord, let me ſome way or other bring honour to thy tender glorious Name among the living, before I come to thee, and adore thee for ever.</p>
               <p>Now Soul, to point thee out thy par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular duty, that liveſt in the ſenſe of the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119879:55"/>favour and love of Chriſt, is more then I deſigned in this brief Treatiſe, only I will minde thee with a word or two, and ſo have done.</p>
               <p>Art thou a Soul that haſt been by the ſtrong arm of the Lord carried through ſome of theſe experiences, as have been ſet forth in this Treatiſe (If thou art a poor Soul not yet attained to this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of comfort and joy, I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to lay down Directions to thee, and what may (by the bleſſing of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with it) uphold thee till theſe wonders ſhall be made good upon thy ſoul: But now to a Soul that in ſome meaſure en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyeth them,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Conſider, that though Jeſus Chriſt hath made ſuch a calm upon thy Spirit, yet know that there's more than enough in thy heart to diſtemper all again, though at preſent kept under, Therefore thou art to look up to the ſame mighty hand, to keep all in peace and in a comfortable frame, as well as at firſt to create it, and to give in new refreſhings, elſe that which is within thee already will decay and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; If Jeſus Chriſt withdraw his hand, all is in a mutiny again; Oh therefore walk humbly and jealouſly before him,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:119879:56"/>and ſtill be committing all to him, and be drawing freſh ſupplies from him, or elſe the ſenſe of this bleſſed calm will grow dead in thee.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Beware how carnal joy mixeth with thy ſpiritual, by fetching in too large ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions from Creature-comforts, whence will follow lightneſſe and vanity of ſpirit, and then comes a Cloud ere thou art a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Be vigilant (as I have before hinted) and diligent in ſuch waies wherein thou haſt ſpeciall communion with God, By which thou ſhalt finde greater wonders by the ſtrong arm of the Lord, then thou haſt yet felt; The danger of this neglect is ſpoken before.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Do not ſit down in a ſlender ſtock of Grace and the Knowledge of Chriſt; There are depths in Chriſt, and depths in thy own heart to be ſearcht, which haply doe yet lie cloſe undiſcerned upon thy ſpirit.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Be in the frequent remembrance of how much is forgiven, and this will raiſe up thy love and zeal, and quicken it when it begins to ſlack.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Beware of venturing on the leaſt ſin, do not ſay 'tis a little one, and thou maiſt
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:119879:56"/>venture, 'twill like an <hi>Achan</hi> diſturb all: The fear and hatred of the leaſt evil maintains a ſolid, ſetled communion with God; vain and carnal company (as hath been ſhewed) dulls a mans ſpirit, as alſo a frothy carriage, and liberall jeſting.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Much might be ſaid, but in a word know, 'Tis the hardeſt work of a Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to manage comfort and aſſurance; The heart, the carnal part of it is apt to be lifted up in it; Indeed a comforted Soul at the firſt coming of it, is apt to conceive, that ſuch a temper can never be loſt; But this is a vanity.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Get the aims of thy heart more raiſed after purity and likeneſſe of God then joy and comfort; To be like God and ſee him at he is, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.2. is the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt aim of a gracious Soul; which the bleſſed, holy God give thee and me to aſpire after, till we ſhall be fully with him, and ſo ſee him as he is to all eternity. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
